<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The market or fayre of vsurers A newe pasquillus or dialogue agaynst vsurye, howe and where it is forbidden, [and] what punyshement belongeth vnto it, [and] whether (for ye mayntenau[n]ce of the necessary trades of marchaundise) it maye be forborne, and ought to be punyshed or not, the chief articles wherof shall apeare vnto the reader in the next pagine. Newely translated out of the high Almaigne, by William Harrys.</title>
            <title>Wucherer Messkram oder Jarmarckt. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06899</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17330</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109830</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845474</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845474</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10377</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06899)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10377)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 56:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The market or fayre of vsurers A newe pasquillus or dialogue agaynst vsurye, howe and where it is forbidden, [and] what punyshement belongeth vnto it, [and] whether (for ye mayntenau[n]ce of the necessary trades of marchaundise) it maye be forborne, and ought to be punyshed or not, the chief articles wherof shall apeare vnto the reader in the next pagine. Newely translated out of the high Almaigne, by William Harrys.</title>
                  <title>Wucherer Messkram oder Jarmarckt. English.</title>
                  <author>Harrys, William.</author>
                  <author>Allen, Edmund, 1519?-1559.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[174] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Steuen Mierdman] Cum priuilegio ad quinquennium,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. M.D.L. [1550]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Der wucherer Messkram oder Jarmarckt.</note>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Edmonde aellen.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L (-L8).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Usury --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10377:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10377:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The market or fayre of Vſurers.</p>
            <p>¶A newe Paſquillus or Dialogue agaynſt Vſurye, howe and where it is forbidden, &amp; what punyſhement belongeth vnto it, &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayntenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the neceſſary trades of marchaundiſe) it maye be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, and ought to be punyſhed or not, The chief Articles wherof ſhall apeare vnto the reader in the next pagine. Newely tranſlated out of the high Almaigne, by William Harrys.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deuter. xxiij.</bibl>
               <p>Thou ſhalt be no vſurer vnto the brother, neither in money nor in fode, nor in any maner thinge that is lent vpon vſurie.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum Priuilegio ad quinquennium. <hi>AN. M.D.L.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:10377:2"/>
            <head>¶The principall matters intreated of in this Dialogue.</head>
            <p>WHether Vſurye (for the mayntenaunce of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie trades of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundiſe) maye be forborne or not.</p>
            <p>Whether vſurie be ſynne altogether or not where and of whome it is forbidden.</p>
            <p>What puniſhement belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to vſurers, out of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of God and alſo of man.</p>
            <p>Beſides this certayne que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as whether a man maye not be maiſter of his owne goodes, and vſe the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to his diſpoſition,
<pb facs="tcp:10377:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> for his profite and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>What vſurye is.</p>
            <p>What an intereſt is.</p>
            <p>What ordre ought to be kepte in felloweſhippes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paignyes. And many other obiections.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10377:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10377:3"/>
            <head>An Epyſtle to the reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Scribes and Pharyſeis and other enemies of Chriſte euer dyd oft tymes atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt him with diuers queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſometime of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours trybute, ſometime of the hygheſt and greateſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the lawe, ſometyme of the ryght way to eternal lyfe, and ſuche lyke. Al whiche que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions they did demaunde not to ſerche out the truthe in any of the ſayde articles whereby to ſattle and grounde theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, nor to be better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in them as though
<pb facs="tcp:10377:4"/> they had doubted in any ſuch matter as they queſtyoned wyth hym of, but onely as the holy text ſayth to tempt hym, and out of his aunſweres to gather ſome matter agaynſt hym whereby to trappe hym, or els to be confyrmed rather in theyr olde and longe before conceyued opinions than to be wythdrawen from them, for they had determined with them ſelues before what they would holde and beleue, and neuer to ſwarne there from nor to ſuffer them ſelues to be perſwaded there from, what ſo euer Chriſte or any of his Apoſtles ſhewe or teache to the contrary. For where as they neyther woulde nor coulde beleue hym to be the heauenly doctor whiche had
<pb facs="tcp:10377:4"/> his commiſſion not from any of the high biſhops or prieſtes, but from the boſom of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of heauen geuyng hym this teſtimony. This is my deare beloued ſonne in whom I delyght and am well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, heare him, heare him, how coulde they receyue or beleue any poynet of hys doctrine: But whatſoeuer he or his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyples ſayde or taught, theyr minde &amp; mindes is being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely feſtyd wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ruſt of igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rans and partely ouercomme with peruerſe obſtynacy they neuer mynded to alter theyr olde corrupt iudgementes &amp; opinions nor to reforme the leaſt errour wherewith they were blynded. In ſo muche as they woulde not ones ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:10377:5"/> their moſte great errours to be any errours at all, but woulde defende them rather as infallyble truthes. And euen at a lyke poynt (the more pytye) is the wycked worlde at this preſent. Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers men are redy to moue dyuers queſtions, ſome of one thyng, and ſome of another thyng, but howe many are there that make their demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and moue theyr pueſtions to the intent to learne or to be better inſtructed: No no, they do it rather eyther of a curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte for ſome colour and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens or els to be confyrmed in theyr former iudgementes and doynges. For if they dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bted of ſuche matters as they queſtion of, they woulde ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyne from doyng the thynge
<pb facs="tcp:10377:5"/> whereof they moue theyr doubt, vntyll ſuche tyme as they were fully reſolued whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they myght lawfully doo it or no. Were it not an vnſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng thyng for a iudge fyrſt to condempne a man to death and than afterwarde to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre whether hys cauſe be worthy of death or no? He ought rather to ſuſpende the ſentens vntyll ſuche tyme as the matter were fully tryed and examyned. Euen ſo there are dyuers that axe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che whether it be lawfull to lende money for increaſe and aduauntage and to vſe vſury and vſans. And in the meane tyme they practyſe the thyng to the vttermooſte they can dryue it, as though it were a matter ſo lawfull as had no
<pb facs="tcp:10377:6"/> maner of doubt in it. O Lord what a blyndnes and peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenes is this, what doo thys men dyffer from the Scribes Pharyſeis and enemyes of Chriſte, the name onely reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that they are and wyll be called Chriſtians the holy Scriptures were neuer more taught, reed nor preached nor better ſet furth then they are at this daye, but let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better, but rather cleane contrary the better preachynge the wors lyuyng, iniquite wyll euer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the vpper hande more and more ſtyll. To paſſe euer other matters were the myndes of men, euer ſo vncharytable or ſo vnſaciable as they be at this daye euen in this lyght of the Goſpell? The more increaſe
<pb facs="tcp:10377:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> God geueth of all thynges, the greater ſtarſenes &amp; dearth is there. The more God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewyth men with ryches the more couetous are they and the more ſhamefull vſury doo they practyſe therewith ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng them ſelues onely as though they were borne for themſelues onely ſaint Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les leſſon teachyng all men to ſeke their neyghbours welth and not their owne is forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. And Iudas leſſon Quid vultis mihi what wyll ye gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, what wyll ye gyue, is lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the fyngers endys.</p>
            <p>And this cauſeth ſo muche mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſery in the worlde as is. Yet it prouoketh Gods vengeans dayly more and more vpon our neckes, I praye God we prouoke it not to muche that
<pb facs="tcp:10377:7"/> it lyghten not vp on vs to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, I pray God euery may refourme hys enormyties in tyme. And ſpecially ſuche as are ſo drowned in coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes that they care not though their euen Chriſten famyſh for honger, as there haue ſome of late bene herd of in this realme, lamentable it is to be hard of. But at whoſe handes ſhall their bloud that ſo peryſhe but at the couetous cormora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes the couetous leaſ mongers the couetous rent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſers, the couetous, I can not tell what ye call them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſers, rakers and ſcrapers of ſo vnſaciable an hundreth mens lyuynges wyl not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce one of them. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue the deuell and al in their handes that the poore muſte
<pb facs="tcp:10377:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> bye of them, they wyll ſell no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng but at their owne pryce. And hereof ſpryngeth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſyng of all thynges.<note place="margin">Agaynſt the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rers.</note> And what Godly lawes ſtatutes or proclamacions ſoeuer be ſet furth by the Chriſten rulers, they can take no place in them though they be founde neuer ſo fauty, they wyll ſhyft oute one waye or other, yf they be iuſtly complayned of to the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, ſome of them wyll bee more redy to excuſe them tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to punyſhe them, he? No he is to honeſt a man to do any ſuch thing. Thus one claweth ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther in the meane tyme deuou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng vp the poore <hi>Tanquam eſcam panis,</hi> as Dauid ſayeth euen as a morſel of bread. And what ſhall I ſaye of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous vſurers, howe many are
<pb facs="tcp:10377:8"/> gnawen to the bones and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vp by them. What make they of the returne of their mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney in one month? But howe lawfully how godly how cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, this lytle treatyſe and dyaloge tranſlated out of the germanis tonge doth teache, yf ſuche as are corrupt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with that kynde of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes wyll be admonyſſhed, they may receiue admonicion and inſtruction thereby. If they wyll not their bloud be vpon their own heades, they can not ſaye but they were taught and warned. To be ſhort God graunt that euery man may conſyder the duty of Chriſten charite and practyſe the ſome, it was neuer more time, it was neuer more nede. If they wyll not let them be
<pb facs="tcp:10377:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſure of this, The oxe is layde at the rote of the tree, the rod is redy made wherewith we ſhall be ſcourged. If any man may be called back at leaſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this vice of vſury by this lytle worck, bothe the wryter and the tranſlatour, ſhall thinke their labours well beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed and ſufficiently recompenſed, God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they may ſo doo Amen. ⁂</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By Edmonde aellen</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:10377:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10377:9"/>
            <head>Paſquillus vnto the vſurers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ere vſurers I cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unced a lyttel befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the laſt fayre to mete with one of yours in eſpeciall, by the way, with whom I had an vnaduiſed communication concerning your ſcience. And foraſmuche as I truſted that it ſhould be profitable to many, if it myght come to your eares, I thought it good to open it vnto you, truſtyng that ye wil take it in good woorth, vntyll God ſend vs better. Thus fare ye well in haſte.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>What make ſhift do I fynde the here.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:10"/>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>A ha frende Paſquill where am I not founde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Go to, thou wilt be founde one daye, where thy frendes woulde thynke full lytell to haue founde the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſo I praye the? where is that as thou thynkeſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>In the deuels chymeny or ſmokinge hole, as I do coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I dare ſaye none other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Oh Paſquill God forbidde it, I truſt not that I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>No? thinkeſt thou ſo? I war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunt
<pb facs="tcp:10377:10"/> the thou arte not lyke vnto hym that ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth behinde the dore. Well take hede, bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue me, it wilbe founde either in the duſt or elles in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwipings. But whither arte thou nowe bounde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Why doeſt thou aſke? kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt thou not, that it is tyme to go to the fayre at Francke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Ah wilt thou thether. Oh howe manye good fellowes wilt thou there cut by the thro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, I thought the harueſt had ben in already, wilt thou nowe fyrſt begynne to reape? But I thinke thou reapeſt both win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Sommer, where thou ſoweſt but lytell. Thou ſhalt one daye, (as I ſayde before) be
<pb facs="tcp:10377:11"/> caried home to the deuell with thy frutes which thou haſt rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped ſo longe. Thinkeſt thou that thou canſt not be forborne at Franckeforth? Beleue me, of a ſuertie, there is many a good man at the fayre, that would rather ſee an olde wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, then the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſo Paſquill? I hurte no man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Neither doeſt thou good to any man, for naught: Whiche thynge many a good man at Franckeforth ſhall fynde ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, ſmally for their profyte.</p>
               <p>What haſt thou elles to do at Franckeforth? Wilt thou ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the ſhepe? It is towarde winter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:11"/>
               <p>What ſhoulde I do there? what do other men there? I care my wares thither, ſell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and go my wayes agayne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>What wares carieſt thou thither?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>I carrie thither gownes of marterns.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>What? carieſt thou thyther gownes of marterns? The deuell taught the that occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. I am ſure thou geueſt them good cheape. But wo vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thoſe that are ſo oppreſſed by the reaſon of wynter, that they haue nede of thy gonnes. I would rather be a colde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll my tethe ſhould clatter in my heade, then I woulde take payne to couer my body wyth
<pb facs="tcp:10377:12"/> thy gownes. I beleue that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny in thy gownes are in ſuche perplexite, that it were no mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueyll though they ſhoulde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyle them bothe behynde and before. But I praye the canſt thou ſell them well? Thou co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt nowe very late.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſh not a wit, I come yet ſoone ynough. Though I ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me thither but at the goynge out of the fayre yet ſhoulde I come tyme ynough. For then haue I moſte commonly the beſt market.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Haſt thou ſo? I perceyue when the marchauntes are bounde homewardes agayne, and feare the colde wether, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are thy gownes of marterns acceptable, howe deare ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:10377:12"/> ſome do bye them. Thou war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt many one with thy gow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in one winter, that they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re afterwardes a colde bothe winter and ſommer. I praye the, why doeſt thou not alſo weare a good thicke, warme gowne, that thou nedeſt not to be couered ſo exceding warm, when men wyll haue a droppe of thy ſweate? But what doeſt thou bye agayne, whan thou haſt taken money.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Nothinge in eſpeciall. I bye certayne ſkynnes of marterns that I maye haue woorke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the next fayre. And the ouerplus of the money whiche I haue then left do I lende vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome good fellowe ſuffering hym to do his profite withall vntyll I come home, and then
<pb facs="tcp:10377:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10377:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10377:14"/> do I receiue it againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>How doeſt thou ſuffre hym to do thy profite with it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>I ſaye his profite and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, what profite can he do me with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Oh God, ſaue me from that profite and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie. I praye God kepe thy gownes, thy mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mey, and thy lendinge out of ny trade: For they ſhould ſone do me ſuch profite and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie therin, that there ſhoulde but littell remayne. I knowe that profite and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie full well good fellowe, tell me not of it I praye the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>I praye the good Paſquil.
<pb facs="tcp:10377:14"/> Let this paſſe, we will talke of other matters, I perceyue right well where about thou goeſt. Thou inuaieſt againſt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurye, &amp; yet knoweſt not what vſurye meaneth. I was aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed as ſoone as euer I ſawe the, for I thought wel ynough that thou wouldeſt not let me alone, becauſe thou art always ready to comptrolle euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Tell vs ſome newes I praye the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Nay heareſt thou, thou art not yet rid of me. Thou muſt at it firſt a litell better. I holde the a grote, I will tel the what vſurye is, except thou wilt not vnderſtande me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Alas good Paſquill, I am nothing afrayde of the. I kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we
<pb facs="tcp:10377:15"/> as muche of that as thou canſt tell me. I wyll geue the worcke ynough, if thou be ſo diſpoſed. But thou wylt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande no reaſon, wherfore I coulde rather be content to talke with the of other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Yea thou knoweſt ſo much of it, that bothe God and man may lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te it. Thou knoweſt ſo many ſhiftes, that a very ſubtill and large inhibition co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning vſurye muſt be made for the, if thou ſhouldeſt not fynde the way to make a great frendſhyppe of moſte abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vſurye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Be content good Paſquill, my knowledge, ſhall neyther diſpleaſe God nor yet man, for
<pb facs="tcp:10377:15"/> I hurte no man with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>In dede the knowledge myght be ſuffered, yf the dede folowed not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſh Paſquill of a trueth thou art ignoraunt of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Thou wilt haue to do with vſurye againſt his wyll, but it is not to be ſcanded as thou thinkeſt, for thou art not expert in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trades of marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe: Howe ſhould tel the what vſurye meaneth? for I thinke thou arte not ſo depely ſene in the holy ſcriptures, nor yet in the lawes, that thou ſhouldeſt knowe ſo properly and exacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcuſſe and to iudge of it. There are many poinctes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longinge to it. Many crye out vpon vſurye, Luther hath alſo
<pb facs="tcp:10377:16"/> writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fearcely againſt it, but it is good to ſee howe they hit it. Yea I knowe certaynely that if thou ſhouldeſt nowe tell me what vſurye is or meaneth, thou ſhuldeſt be to ſeke in it, I omitte that thou ſhouldeſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actely diſpute of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Wel go to, I haue not ſtudied in holy ſcripture in dede, very much nor yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it poſſible for me to reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, vnderſtond or to no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre all &amp; ſynguler inuencions and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, of the, and of the theuiſh, deuelyſhe commyng, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till felloweſhippe, yet dare I vndertake to tell the what vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry is, neither wil I miſſe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſtrawe breadth from the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſcripture, and the true ſenſe thereof. But I praye the, haſt
<pb facs="tcp:10377:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> thou redde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Luthers booke whereof thou haſt made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion? yf thou haue, I doubte not but he hath ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly told it the. And although it pleaſe not the, I thynke that Luther wrote it not to thintent that it ſhoulde pleaſe the and ſuche as thou arte. I haue hearde dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other whiche ſayde that he vnderſtode it not. But I thinke ye wil not vnderſtande it. Yf he haue not noted, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and confuted all your excu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes and ſhifting holes (as it is impoſſible for any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know or to remember them all) yet hath he laide ſuch a foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ye can not ouerthrowe it, no though ye knewe and had the ſubtiltie and craft of all the deuilles in hell. Therfore it ſkilleth not, although thou and
<pb facs="tcp:10377:17"/> ſuche lyke helhoundes be not pleaſed with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>What good fellowe, thou ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt not to call me, and my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortes helhoundes, becauſe I am not pleaſed with Luthers booke, for I knowe if thou thy ſelfe ſhouldeſt rede it and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre it accordyngly, thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not be pleaſed with it, for he will haue it in al poinctes ſo ſtrayt as a lyne. But he hath not wayed it with further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſement.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>What I praye the, hath he drawen the nette to ſtreight for the? thinkeſt thou ſo? thou thoughteſt he ſhoulde haue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured the, the breadth of a finger, that thou mighteſt find a ſtertyng hole, as thou doeſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Yea I wis is it drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to nar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe &amp; to ſtraight, as alſo the wiſe Iuriſtes of Wittenbergh diſputed of late, that yf a man ſhould take fyue or ſyxe in the hundred by the yere, it ſhoulde be ſinne and vſurye: Thynke ye that it was not well ſpoken of wyſe men?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Yea I haue alſo hearde of the ſame, Art thou not pleaſed with it? Would to God that that man whiche diſputed the ſame had ſo muche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might write of it, his vnwyſe reaſon ſhoulde ſo ſpreade it out, that thou and all thy felloweſhyppe ſhoulde haue yet leſſe pleaſure in it. I praye the thinkeſt thou that it is ſo vnwyſely ſpoken, to ſaye that but fyue or ſyxe of
<pb facs="tcp:10377:18"/> the hundred is ſynne and vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye? Howe doeth it then pleaſe the, that the ſame diſputacion affirmeth moreouer, ſaing that if a man take a draught of cold water more then he hath lent, it is and ought to be called vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye? Howe thinkeſt thou by that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhould I thinke by it? It is folye. They vnderſtonde it not, where ſhould they haue learned it? I would gladly rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon with one of them of it. And Paſquill, if I ſhoulde reaſon with the of it at large, I would tell the ſo muche, and laye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſuche inuincible argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and concluſions, that thou ſhouldeſt be conſtrayned thy ſelfe to graunte and to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe, that vſurye maye not be
<pb facs="tcp:10377:18"/> tyed vp ſo ſhorte nor be ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended, how ſore ſoeuer thou be nowe againſte it. And woulde alſo decently proue vnto the that ſuche vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye (as thou doeſt call it) is no ſinne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>If I <abbr>had</abbr> nowe foure eares more then I haue, I would ſet them all open with noſe and mouth to herke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore go to with it, &amp; ſpare not. If thou couldeſt perſuade me that Luther and the high lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned and experte Iuriſtes dyd not vnderſtande it, and that ſuche vſurie were no ſynne, I would holde ſomwhat of the, and would then alſo playe the vſurer in ſuche ſorte that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge ſhoulde cauſe me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayne it, ſauing lacke of head
<pb facs="tcp:10377:19"/> money.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>But I ſpeake not of very great vſurye, as thou thinkeſt, but of a reaſonable and decent gaynes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Thy reaſonable and decent is vnto the younge occupiers and beginners, euen as the pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yenge of the catte is vnto the mouſe. But I praye the ſaye on, thynkeſt thou that vſurye ought not to be ſo ſtraightely tyed, and that it is no ſinne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Wel ſeing thou haſt a minde to it, I wyll talke with the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of it, and fyrſt I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude on this maner. Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer maye not be forborne for the mayntenaunce of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:10377:19"/> welth both in citie and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, of mutuall felloweſhyp, &amp; of all maner of neceſſaries per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynynge to the natural life of man, is not imputed vnto vs of God for ſynne, yea and the hyer powers ought not onely not to hynder it, but alſo to fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der and helpe to maintayne it. For God wil haue the mutual conuerſation among men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued and entretayned in due ordre. Now it is manifeſt that vſurye can not be forborne for the vpholdynge of the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: Therefore can it not be ſynne, &amp; reaſon requireth that it be let alone,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>C ae ff<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de Vſuris pertotu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> but it ſhall be founde contrary</note> according as the temporall lawes writen haue letten it paſſe, as I am infour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>The fyrſt parte, wyll I paſſe
<pb facs="tcp:10377:20"/> ouer and let it remayne in his force,<note place="margin">Exemp. ſunt in Deut. <hi>C. 18.</hi> Vbi iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deis ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialiter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceditur. Vſurari. et in Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, <hi>1.</hi> Re. <hi>21</hi> et in Euangel. Marci. C. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> for doubteles whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer among men can not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, ſhall not be imputed of God for ſynne, for elles therof ſhoulde followe a greate incon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenience, wherfore I wyl here make no farther ſearce of it.</p>
               <p>But the other, where thou ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeſt, that vſurye can not be for borne for the ſame, I do not yet ſufficiently vnderſtande, neither wyll I graunte it the, oneles thou infourme me bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it. If thou canſt proue it me, I will graunte the the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence the thirde parte, and do as I haue ſaide before. But as longe as thou doeſt not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the ſame, I wyll in no wyſe graunt the the third parte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>That vſury can not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne,
<pb facs="tcp:10377:20"/> wyll I proue on this wyſe.</p>
               <p>The trades of Marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe can not be forborne. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo thoſe thynges that helpe to vpholde &amp; maintayne the trades of marchaundyſe can not be forborne.</p>
               <p>That the trade of marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diſe can not be forborne is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. For euery huſbandman can not runne thither where all thynges neceſſary growe and are made. Neither is ther any lande, that hath al thinges neceſſary for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therfore muſt there nedes be ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye all maner of neceſſaryes, from lande to lande and from one contrey to another. As it is manifeſt in the lawes.</p>
               <p>Therfore muſt it alſo follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we, that the thinge can not be
<pb facs="tcp:10377:21"/> forborne whiche helpeth too maintayne the trades of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundiſe.<note place="margin">Calliſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>usin l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>j ff. de Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis. Ex pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tonc. Vide Dn. Budcum hic pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre.</note> For lyke as I can not forbeare an houſe in wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, euen ſo can I not forbeare the thynge whiche ſuſtayneth and kepeth vp the houſe from fallyng. In lyke manner, if the thynge be not, or elles ceaſſeth, whiche beareth and ſuſteyneth the trades of marchaundiſe, then muſt alſo the trades of marchaundyſe fall and ceaſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Thou nedeſt not to make half ſo many wordes. I knowe aforehande, that whanſoeuer thou affirmeſt any thynge ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſome fondacion, thou ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt all vauntage that can bee ſought. That the trades of marchaundiſe can not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, this do I knowe very
<pb facs="tcp:10377:21"/> wel. I knowe alſo on the other parte, that dyuers trades of marchaundiſe might as well be forborne, as ſome cannot be forborne. Whereof I coulde ſhewe the ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t proues, but we wyll not nowe ſo farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe from oure purpoſe. I knowe (I ſaye) precyſely, that the trades of marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe can not be forborne. I do alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, that the thynge can not bee forborne whiche ſuſteyneth and vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the neceſſarye trades of marchaundiſe. But what wilt thou conclude of this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Soft I pray the, thou ſhalt heare it well ynough. I proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de nowe, ſayenge.</p>
               <p>What ſoeuer ſuſteyneth and vpholdeth the neceſſarye tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:10377:22"/> of marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe, can not be forborne, neither is it any ſinne lendyng and borrowynge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth the neceſſary trades of marchaundiſe.</p>
               <p>Therfore can not lendynge and borrowinge be forborne, neither is it any ſynne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Concedo totum argumentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I graunte all the whole argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But ſee, howe connyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he goeth aboute the matter, euen as the catte goeth about a meaſe of hoate potage. Oh, I perceiue ſo pretely wherabout thou goeſt. If thou get muche by this, I am ſory for it. But I praye the, go to, ſaye on, let vs ſe what thou wilt make of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhould I make of it? I wil nowe procede further, and
<pb facs="tcp:10377:22"/> conclude on this wiſe.</p>
               <p>Lendynge and borrowinge may not be forborne, neither is it any ſynne.</p>
               <p>Wherefore alſo the occaſion of lendynge and borrowynge, and the thynge whiche vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth lendyng and borrowyng, may not be forborne, neither is it any ſynne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Ha ha he, this maketh me to laughe, I praye the where haſt thou learned this goodly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſt in ſo ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhynge ſmothely ouer newe market heath? For thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt haue come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nere to the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter a great deale. But thou wilt ſaye a good foundacion for thy matter, for the buylding is heauy, and hath muche nede of it, but digge not to depe, or els
<pb facs="tcp:10377:23"/> thou ſhalt fynde water. Oh what a ſortee of dogges flyes haſt thou about the, although it be not about midſomer. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dideſt thou euer heare me ſaye that lendyng and borrowinge is euill?<note place="margin">Luc. Vi. Deu xxV Matt. <hi>V.</hi> Eccliſia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> xxViii.</note> Is it not commanded in the holy ſcripture? If ſo be that prayſe vnto the lendinge and borrowyng, howe ſhoulde I diſpraiſe the cauſe of lending and borrowyng? But on I praye the, I wyl mete with the anone, oute with it, go to, I wil tell the anone of that occaſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Well, then will I procede, &amp; ſaye for a concluſion.</p>
               <p>The occaſion of lending and borrowyng ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be forborne, neither is it any ſynne.</p>
               <p>Vſury is occaſion of lending and borrowinge.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Therfore can not vſurye be forborne, neither is that alſo any ſynne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Ergo, ideo, igitur, quare, quamobrem propterca. Here of followeth vſurye ſo mighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; cleaueth ſo faſt to lendinge and borrowinge, that no Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gician is able to moue the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence neither is there any Alchimiſt ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge, nor any water ſo ſtronge, that is able to ſeperate them. What waye ſhal I now tourne me ſelfe? There haſt thou hit me in dede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art full of pratynges and mockes, but yet thou canſt not leape ouer it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>No in dede if a loode of haye
<pb facs="tcp:10377:24"/> ſtode in my waye I could not, but I praye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who hath taught the that high logike? wher haſt thou ſtudied it? Where haſt thou redde that vſurye is the occaſion of lendinge and borro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge? ſpecially of that len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge and borrowynge which is magnified and prayſed of the ſcripture. I thought thou had<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt vnderſtanded me, that I ſpeake of lendinge and borro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge whiche the ſcripture prayſeth.<note n="a" place="margin">Eccli. <hi>29. C.</hi>
                  </note> But I muſt tell it the playne. There are two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of lendynges and borro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wings. The one is that which is done of Chriſtian charite &amp; mercifulnes frely without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of any rewarde. The other is that whiche is done of couetouſnes for gaynes and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes ſake. Whether of both
<pb facs="tcp:10377:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> theſe (thinkeſt thou) is praiſed of holy ſcripture? Whether of both (thinkeſt thou) can not be forborne? I am ſure that len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; borrowinge for nought of more loue and mercy,<note place="margin">D.C. <hi>29,</hi> Eccli.</note> with out reſpect of any rewarde, is prayſed in the ſcripture. And this maye not be forborne, this alſo is not onely no ſynne, but a Chriſtian good worke, which God will rewarde, the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whereof is the Chriſtian loue, not to be forborne nor diſpray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for ſhe is a tree ful of many good frutes. And here do I graunte the, that this lending and borrowynge with his oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion maye not be forborne, &amp; that it is no ſynne. But where wilt thou become with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other lending &amp; borrowynge which procedeth of couetouſnes for
<pb facs="tcp:10377:25"/> lucres ſake? Thinkeſt thou that this alſo maye not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, and that it is no ſynne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>It is certayne that it maye not be forborne. Seynge then that it can not be forborne, it can not be ſynne, nor yet hys occaſion, wherfore my conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion muſt nedes ſtande ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Well if thou canſt proue me, that ſuche lendynge whiche is done for lucres ſake can not be forborne, then muſt I byte in a foure apple, and yelde me ſelfe, to be almoſte ouercome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>That it cannot be forborne, it is euident, thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeſt thy ſelf, and it is alſo manifeſt, that lendinge and borrowynge can
<pb facs="tcp:10377:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> not be forborne, &amp; nowe, thou makeſt two kyndes of lending and borrowynge, wherewith I am content, neither do I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprayſe the ſame diuiſion. But when the one ceaſſeth, if ſo be that lendinge and borrowinge ſhall continue then muſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nedes ſuccede. Thou ſeeſt with thyne owne eyes, that no man will lende for nought, &amp; there muſte nedes be lending and borrowynge what waye ſoeuer it come. Therfore muſt nedes the other ſuccede in the rowme of the firſte, and can in no wiſe be forborne. Nowe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge it can not be forborne, the thynge ought alſo to be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red whiche is the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by lendynge and borrowynge is maintayned, leaſt occupieng decaye and peryſh by the, both
<pb facs="tcp:10377:26"/> in citie and towne as is afore mencioned. For certayne it is, that yf lendynge and borro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winge ſhould ceaſſe, occupieng muſt nedes decaye and fal, and many men ſhould peryſhe and dye for honger. If then le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding for aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage were forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or were made ſo greate a ſinne, it ſhoulde ceaſſe, and lendynge for nought is ceaſſed and gone already, what an hurlyburly &amp; inconuenience ſhoulde followe of it maye be eaſely perceiued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Beholde I praye the, who would haue beleued that thou haddeſt ben ſo good an archer, that thou ſhouldeſt ſo iuſtely haue hit the pricke? Thou haſt hit it euen as he that woulde ſtryke the cowe on the heade, and hit her on the tayle. I mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaill
<pb facs="tcp:10377:26"/> whether thou doeſt wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deceyue the ſelfe or that thy maiſter the deuell hath ſo blynded the, that thou canſt or wilt not vnderſtande thy ſelfe what thou ſpeakeſt. Thy mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge is this as I vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de thy wordes, foraſmuche as no man wyll lende for nought, lendyng for aduauntage muſt nedes be ſuffered and not bee counted for ſynne, that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary felloweſhyp and occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienge amonge men maye bee entretayned. What meaneth this elles? then, no man will do good, therefore muſt God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre all abhominacion, and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te it for no ſynne, or els he ſhould be fayne to be in heauen alone. Or whan the wolfe hath eaten one ſhepe, whyle he wyll not be ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented, he doth not amiſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:10377:27"/> though he take another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> either the deuell hym ſelfe hath blyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the, and ſpoyled the of thy wittes, or elles thou wilt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des go the wrong way againſt the deuilles wyll. A blynde ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye fele, howe this agreeth, no man will do good, therefore muſt wronge dealynge be pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed. Thou ſayeſt, and alas it is to true, that no man will lende for nought. But what is the cauſe? Is it not that deteſtable vnſaciable couetouſnes? If that were not the firſt lending ſhoulde not ceaſſe but followe mightely. But when couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes is preſent, and doth hinder it, is it then Goddes ſeruice? Wilt thou therefore conclude, couetouſnes hyndereth Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charite, therfore muſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes haue his courſe?
<pb facs="tcp:10377:27"/> Yea ſayeſt thou I graunt that it were better and more godly done, to lende for nought, but ſeyng the ſame is not done, the other can not be forborne, and ſeynge it can not be forborne, the occaſion maye not be taken awaye, leaſt it be daſſhed alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Lo thou putteſt here two partes, the one that len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge for aduauntage can not be forborne, the other is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence wherfore the ſame is no ſynne. So that thou repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt all that thou haſt ſayde. Nowe wyll I aunſwere the more playner. Firſt that the len<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge for vſurye can not be for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>borne doeſt thou proue by this, becauſe that lendinge without rewarde ceaſſeth, and that yet for all that lendynge and borro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>winge may not be away. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vpon
<pb facs="tcp:10377:28"/> I haue aunſwered the that wronge dealynge can not be good, becauſe no man wyll deale vprightely. Therfore muſt thou haue a reſpect to the occaſion of the ſame ceaſſinge, &amp; let it be ſynne, namely couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and then ſhalt eaſely iudge the other parte, that is to ſaye, whether lendynge for aduaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tage by ſynne or not. And I thynke alſo that thou wilt iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge thy ſelfe that all is not well, ſauyng only that neceſſite cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the to affirme the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For thou ſayeſt that nede re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quireth it to be ſuffered, leaſt lendinge and borrowynge do decaye. Here will I aſke the a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Who is it that can not forbeare this lendynge vpon vſurye? Thinkeſt thou that thoſe pore fellowes whiche are
<pb facs="tcp:10377:28"/> in neceſſitie can not forbeare it? Yes yes very well, yf they can not forbeare lending, they may forbeare vſurye ſo muche the better. Yea ſayeſt thou, if they can not forbeare lendyng then muſt alſo vſury nedes haue his courſe. Yea they are ſory ynough for it, that it hath hys courſe, for they coulde forbeare it well ynough. Who is it then that can not forbeare it? The vſurers? Yea verely, becauſe they can not be filled nor ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, elles coulde they forbeare it well ynough. Therfore maye vſurye on euery ſyde be forborne well ynough, neither is there any neceſſite that can make it good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Paſquill thou doeſt not well vnderſtande me. Howe be it
<pb facs="tcp:10377:29"/> thou haſt ſayd ſo much in dede that it maye be perceiued, that the faute is nowhere but in the will. And indede a man might as well lende for nought as for lukers ſake, if he woulde do it. But I wil be here, thou talkeſt muche of Chriſten loue, but it wilbe longe or thou ſhalt bring it into all marchauntes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do I ſuppoſe, that vſurye can not be cleane taken awaye in the trades of marchaundiſe. For then thoſe trades muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caye remedyles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I vnderſtande the well and fyne, nowe better then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Thou wilt graunte me I am ſure, that it is not wel done not to lende for nought.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:29"/>
               <p>I graunte in dede that it were better and Godlyer, yf men dyd ſo. But that it ſhould be ſo euill done to take a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable rewarde for it, this can not I beleue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Well that ſhall come after: I wyll not nowe digreſſe from thy purpoſe, but will reaſone with the of that, where thou thynkeſt, that vſurye may not be whole taken awaye, becauſe of this neceſſite, that occupie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſhoulde fall and decaye. Of the ſynne wil we talke afterward. If vſurye were nowe forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den quyte and cleane, in ſuche wyſe that no man durſt take any more then he had lent (I ſpeake of vſurye and not of ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes whiche maye be redemed agayne) what thynkeſt thou
<pb facs="tcp:10377:30"/> woulde folowe of it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſſhe, that is impoſſible to be done, what ſhoulde follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of it, no man woulde lende or truſte any more to other, &amp; ſo muſt occupienge nedes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, would to God that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny of thoſe trades of occupie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g had neuer bene inuented nor brought vp. But heareſt thou, I muſt ſomewhat tell the of that lendynge and borrowing whiche maye not be forborne. There muſt nedes be lendyng and truſting, to thyntent that many a pore fellowe maye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue where withall to begynne, truthe it is that many one is able to occupie for the profite
<pb facs="tcp:10377:30"/> of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welth although he haue not alwaies ready mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney. But if it were forboden (as in dede it is forboden ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently) that no man ſhould ſell his wares whiche he truſteth, any dearer, then he doth when he ſelleth them for ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, thinkeſt thou that lending and truſtynge woulde vtterly decaye? no verely. The great occupiers woulde neuer ſuffre that lacke in their occupienge. They ſhoulde not alwayes fynde ſuche marchauntes as would brynge them great bag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges full of dubbell ducates.</p>
               <p>Wherfore yf they woulde ſell their wares they ſhoulde bee fayne to truſte then as well as nowe. And although they woulde not truſte many one whome they truſte nowe, yet
<pb facs="tcp:10377:31"/> woulde they truſte ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rather then they woulde kepe their wares &amp; loſe their freſhe occupienge. And then muſt ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny a man occupie as farre as his purſe woulde reache, and ſtretche out his legges accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the length of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlet. He muſt occupie ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the leſſe, go fayre and eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not flye before his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were growen. Then ſhoulde he alſo haue this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage, that he ſhoulde bye ſo muche the better cheape, &amp; ſhoulde not nede to take nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty, olde, myngled and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable wares, wherby he might warraunt them agayne vnto other, and nede not to deceiue any man. Whiche ſhoulde be vnto him an occaſion of a good name whereby his occupieng
<pb facs="tcp:10377:31"/> ſhould greatly increace. Now adayes, yf a man be truſted, he muſt geue ſo muche more in euery pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and beſydes this he muſt take naughty and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wares, whereby the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people is enhaunced and deceiued. For he muſt nedes ſell hys falſe borrowed wares agayne ſo muche the dearer, if he wyll recouer his head mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and haue a lyuing by it. Wherfore if this enhauncynge were forboden, the marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhoulde be conſtrayned to lende and to truſte eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as well then as nowe, yf they woulde occupie, and lendyng and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowynge ſhould then kepe his courſe better and more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly than it doth nowe.</p>
               <p>Paraduenture thou wilt ſaye, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be done, who ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:10377:32"/> looke vpon it, or who can be in all occupacions, and at all bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaines? To this anſwere, that the borrowers and ſuche as ſhoulde be truſted, woulde ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke good hede to it, and woulde alſo inquire diligently, howe wares are ſolde for ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Therefore this is ſure, that although ſuche enhaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynge and rayſyng of prices in lendynge or truſtynge were ſtrayghtely forbode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet ſhoud good trades of marchaundyſe and occupatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s kepe their cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe neuertheleſſe. And yf thou thynkeſt that the occupiers woulde alſo kepe vp their wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res for ready money, thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeſt be ſure, that yf one come &amp; bryng ready money, yf ſo be that the occupier wyll not let hym haue hys wares for a rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb facs="tcp:10377:32"/> pryce, he wyll go to an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other, whiche wilbe glad to let hym haue it for a price reaſona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. Whoſoeuer wyll make mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney of hys wares, muſt alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue money for them. The marchauntes and ſellers are expert ynough in that feate, yf a man come vnto them &amp; bring a bagge of money in his hand, they are loth to ſende hym a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye.</p>
               <p>In lyke maner we conclude of lending. Where as one mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaunt le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to another, or a riche Iewe hauyng much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney lendeth to this man or to that man for money. If this were forbidden, as in dede it is forboden in all lawes, that no-man ſhoulde take more againe then he had lent, ſhoulde occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienge then decaye? No for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſothe.
<pb facs="tcp:10377:33"/> One good neighboure woulde lende to another ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles a crowne or twayne at his nede. If then one ryche man woulde not lende to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo muſt the nedy leaue muche pryde, deceyte and brag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynge. If the ryche would not lende vnto the pore marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and ſpecially to yonge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners, then muſt euery man order him ſelfe thereafter, and occupie faire &amp; ſoftely, he muſt not crye ho before he were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the dyche, nor make larger cloakes then the cloth woulde geue, and it were better and more profitable for the occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers and the common welth, that it is nowe when vſurye &amp; ſuche greate lendyng is occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied.</p>
               <p>It were better for the occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers,
<pb facs="tcp:10377:33"/> for then ſhoulde not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that is not worth one hundred crownes be ſo ready to borrowe for .iij. thouſande crownes wares, truſtynge to the vſurers. Item it chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth many tymes when a man hath occupied for a ſeaſon, and hath bene truſted of many an honeſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which haue lent hym their wares, that an vſurer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth after them, and eateth hym vp cleane, ſo that of fleſſhe and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes he becommeth yron, in the deuils name, and payeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge to noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And though it were not greatly for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great occupiers which lende ſo muche money vpon vſurye, yet haue they no nede of it, neyther ſhoulde their oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupienge decaye by the reaſon thereof, and it ſhoulde be for
<pb facs="tcp:10377:34"/> the commodite of the meane ſorte, that they ſhould not be ſo deceiued, and alſo for the yong beginners, for then they ſhuld learne to take hede to them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues, and to occupie after their abilitie, that they ſhoulde not clyme ſo hygh in one yere, that that they ſhoulde afterwarde be conſtrayned to fall ſo muche the hier with ſhame, they ſhuld alſo knowe their gaynes, and that they gette it for them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and not for the vſurers. It ſhoulde be for the common weith, that God were not ſo of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fended with vſurye, that there chaunced not ſo many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of decayed marchauntes, that euery man muſt occupie according to his purpoſe, &amp; not aboue hys abylite, leaſt hee might bee occaſioned to take
<pb facs="tcp:10377:34"/> muche vpon vſurye, by the rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon whereof he ſhould be fayne to rayſe the pryces of his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res agayne, and to ſell ſo much the dearer. If princes and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties had not one or twayne that were ryche alone and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred men pore or more the hygh Potentates and alſo their poore commons ſhoulde not ſo fore be burthened in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of nede, they ſhoulde learne alſo to auoide ſome daungers. Wherfore it were better that vſurye were forboden, for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye occupienge ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne neuertheles in his cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe. And although it gaue the occupiers a blowe, (for many of them ſhoulde not haue ſo great a trade, neither ſhoulde there bee ſo many occupiers) yet can not I perceyue wherin
<pb facs="tcp:10377:35"/> it ſhoulde be preiudiciall or hur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tefull to the common welth. For it ſhoulde profite the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth in thoſe thynges whiche I haue recited before.</p>
               <p>Parauenture thou wilt ſay vnto me, it is a thynge whiche perchaunce myght be brought to paſſe in ſuche thynges as ſhalbe done &amp; contracted here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, but howe ſhould it agree with that whiche is in occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienge all ready? One man is indebted to another, euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wylbe payde, if his debter ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no money there muſt nedes be ſome body to lende hym, for his creditour hath made hys rekenynge vpon it. Wherfore if vſurye were forbydden, he ſhoulde fynde no man that woulde lende hym.</p>
               <p>To this I aunſwere. That
<pb facs="tcp:10377:35"/> one muſt beare with another from the leaſt vnto the mooſt, for they maye tarye well ynough. If they will not,<note place="margin">Eccli. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> they may go their wayes from the doores. If complaynte be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de then muſt the hyer powers helpe and counſayle according as the matter requireth. Yea I can be contente to graunte that it woulde geue the occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers a blowe, but wherein ſhoulde it hynder the common welth? The marchauntes alſo ſhoulde fynde the meanes wel ynough, that the trades of oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupienge ſhoulde not be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hindred by it. But they let it not come to that, for it woulde ſeme very greuous them, but if it were ones put in vre, no man ſhoulde fele any hurte by it except the vſurers, neyther
<pb facs="tcp:10377:36"/> ſhoulde any man be the worſe by it ſauyng the chief marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and that coulde make no greate matter. For within the ſpace of a yeare or twayne it might be brought to that paſſe that all ſhoulde be forgotten, and there ſhould be an vpright and true dealynge in al trades of occupienge. In dede it is a greate matter to ſpeake of, yea and I knowe right well that all marchauntes thynke it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, but yet if they were ſo diſpoſed, hauynge a mynde to it, and would helpe thereunto, they ſhould finde it otherwiſe. This do I not ſpeake becauſe I woulde teache the hyer po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers what they ſhoulde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidde, or becauſe I thinke that lendynge and truſting may be altogether forborne. But to
<pb facs="tcp:10377:36"/> ſhewe the my minde howe vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye may be right wel forborne, and that, although it were ſhar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pely forbydden, the common welth ſhoulde not be onely not hyndered by it, but alſo greate<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly furthered.<note place="margin">Sicut ipſe Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor facitin L. I. § fin. C. de. cad. tollen</note> And although it were ſomewhat preiudiciall to certayne fatte Cobbes, yet ought rather a reſpecte to bee hadde to the furtheraunce of the common welth, then to the priuate welth of certayne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and ſynfull perſons. Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma GOD forbiddeth vs no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge that for the maintenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of a decent order and for the neceſſite of mutuall conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion &amp; lyuinge betwene man &amp; man can not be forborne. But God hath forbidden vſurye.<note place="margin">Vt infra patebit.</note> Wherfore it is certayne and cleare, that it maye well be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne.
<pb facs="tcp:10377:37"/> Alſo that the aboliſhing of it ſemeth to be ſuche a buſy pece of worke, is for lacke of a good will towardes the ſame, for the faute of it is nowhere elles but in the will, wherfore I ſaye, that the obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the great occupiers and ſpecially of the vſurers is nothynge worth, whiche ſaye, that vſury can not be abrogated, though there be neuer ſo much cryeng and writinge againſt it, becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe that for the maintenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the trades of marchaundiſe it can not be forborne. In dede they that be vſurers, and ſuch as haue a profite by it, thinke that they can not forbeare it, yea many of them (I thynke) would go nygh to hange them ſelues, yf it ſhould be forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or rather more then forbidden,
<pb facs="tcp:10377:37"/> but the common welth might forbeare it wel ynough, for the neceſſary trades &amp; occupie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, ſhoulde kepe their courſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles, as farrefurth as they are neceſſary and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the common welth, and can not be forborne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Of a truthe Paſquill thou art able to bringe a man in a doubte. In dede it is true that the faulte is but in the will, for elles it coulde not be ſo impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to be done, But to brynge men to this will is very harde to be done. There are very ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny of this opinion, yea and I my ſelfe haue bene of this iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, that vſurye ought to be permitted, and not to be abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyſhed, becauſe of the trades of marchaundiſe. But nowe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely
<pb facs="tcp:10377:38"/> I knowe not what I ſhoulde ſaye. Truely I wyl lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke better vpon the matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Remember thy ſelfe and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye aboute it, and thou ſhalt fynde that the faute is in the will onely, and not in the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilite, as pertayninge to the marchauntes. I knowe that not a fewe, vnto whome this our communication ſhal come, wil be very ſore offended with al, thinkinge that heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would fall, and the worlde peryſhe, yf vſurye ſhoulde be abolyſhed &amp; taken away, notwithſtanding euery man is bounde to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, to ſaye, and to do the beſt for the profite of the common welth. But if there were any wyſe man among them being perſwaded and certified by
<pb facs="tcp:10377:38"/> hys learnynge that vſurye myght not be forborne, for the mayntenaunce of occupieng &amp; for the profite of the common welth, that woulde write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me? Howe ſhoulde I do then? But I do not greately feare it, I truſt to God that I ſhall gette neuer a white heare for it. For they are aſſhamed of their occupacion, neither wyll any of them lyghtely crye Cuckowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>No faith Paſquill, thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not to feare that matter neuertheles yf it ſhould chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, whiche God forbidde, I doubte not, but thou wouldeſt fynde an aunſwere for hym.</p>
               <p>But I will loke better vpon it my ſelfe, and at this tyme we wyl procede, and talke further
<pb facs="tcp:10377:39"/> of the matter that I ſpake of before. I will graunte the that it were more Godly and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenly done, if one would lende to another for nought, yea I permitte alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſurye myght be forborne for a nede. But thinkeſt thou, I praye the, that a man is ſo bounde to lende for nought, that it ſhould be ſinne, yf he did it not? Maye not one vſe his goodes for his moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauntage? Who will compell a man to lende awaye his goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des for nought, whiche he myght occupie hym ſelfe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Thou putteſt here thre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Firſt, whether a man be bounde to lende vnto his neighbour: Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee ſynne to take any thynge for it. Thirdely whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:10377:39"/> a man maye not occupye his goodes to his moſte ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage. To the firſt wyll I anſwere the with Doctor Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall powers doth not compell the to lende awaye thyne owne, wherfore alſo the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall powers doth not correcte the if thou do it not, neither can they ſaye that thereby thou haſt offended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But whether thou be bounde to it before God, &amp; whether it be ſinne before god, nedeſt thou not to aſke me, for it is written. Whoſoeuer hath this worldes good,<note place="margin">i. Iohn. iij.</note> and ſeeth his brother haue nede, &amp; ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp his compaſſion from hym, howe abydeth the loue of God in hym. Is not loue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded in many places of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſcripture? and alſo her wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes?
<pb facs="tcp:10377:40"/> Sayth not the ſcripture,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Ioh. iiij</note> beloued, yf God ſo loued vs, that he gaue his onely begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne for vs, and ſent hym into the worlde, that we might ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue through hym, we ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to loue one another. If we loue one another, God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in vs.<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> Item this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement haue we of hym, that he whiche loueth God ſhoulde loue his brother alſo.<note place="margin">Leuit. xix</note> Item thou ſhalt loue thy neighboure as thy ſelfe.<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>V.</hi>
                  </note> Item ſe that ye lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue one another with a pure harte feruently.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Pet. <hi>I.</hi>
                  </note> Item, this is my commaundement, that ye loue one another.<note place="margin">Iohn. xV.</note> Lo, thou art bounde to loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe, arte thou not then bounde to helpe hym to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaill hym, and to profyte hym, as thy ſelfe? Yea yf thou muſt
<pb facs="tcp:10377:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> do to other as thou wouldeſt be done to if thou were in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſite,<note place="margin">Luc. <hi>VI.</hi> Mat. Vij.</note> and yf thou mighteſt be holpen with money, and kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that thy neighbour had ynough, wouldeſt thou not be glad that he woulde helpe and ſuccour the?<note place="margin">Rom. xij.</note> Thynkes thou that loue is called the fulfilling of the lawe in vayne? Wylt thou then be a Chriſtian? wilt thou walke in the lawe? Wilt thou dwell in God? And wilt not abyde and walke in loue? Sayth not the lorde Chriſte,<note place="margin">I. Iohn iiij Mat. <hi>V.</hi> Deut. xV.</note> tourne not awaye from hym that woulde borrowe of the? Item. When one of thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you is waxed pore ſe that thou harden not thyne harte, nor ſhut to thyne hande from thy pore brother, but ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thyne hande to hym and lende
<pb facs="tcp:10377:41"/> hym ſufficiente for hys nede whiche he hath. Lo thynkeſt thou that thou arte not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently commaunded to lende vnto thy brother? Thynkeſt thou yet that thou arte not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to it? Yea is not by this alſo thy ſeconde queſtion ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently anſwered, where thou demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt whether it be ſinne to take ought for it? Beholde, yf the lendynge of a Chriſten man, be a dede of charite and mercy, ſhould then the ſellyng of thy wares to a man for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney be alſo a dede of charite? What doeſt thou geue hym for goddes ſake I praye the?<note place="margin">Luc. vi.</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yeth not Chriſte, that thou ſhuldeſt le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de loking for nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g therof again? He ſaith lokinge for nothing, I omitte taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing. Shuld this alſo be a Godly worke, when thou len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb facs="tcp:10377:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> &amp; art payde dere ynough for thy labour? Do not ſinners alſo lende ſynners, as Chriſte ſaith in the ſame place? Wilt thou aſke yet whether it bee ſynne to take any more than thou haſt lent? Is it not vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye? Do noth both the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and temporall lawes call all that vſurye, whatſoeuer is taken aboue the head ſumme? <note n="a" place="margin">i. iiij. iiij. q C pleri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>. Cum. c. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quen. A. xx. C. de Vſuris in Sum. ae. Communi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter.</note> Not onely the money which is that aboue, but alſo whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer it be, <note n="b" place="margin">D. xiiij. q. iij. C. ſi fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neraueris. C. ſequen. <hi>D. C.</hi> ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>. &amp;c. fin.</note> as meate, drinke, rayme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cloth or any thing els. Yea alſo the only deſyre or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe to haue any lucre or gaynes by it is vſurye, and whoſoeuer lendeth ought after this ſorte is called an vſurer in the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual lawes. c. For it is written, Mutuum date nihil inde ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes. Se that ye le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de loking
<pb facs="tcp:10377:42"/> for nothynge thereof agayne.<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>D.C.</hi> Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerarius. et de Vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ris C. Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuluit. <hi>D.</hi> C. <hi>6.</hi> Luc. Excipe ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus in. <hi>6.</hi> Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus. c. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubriter. et i. Ex de Vſurisquo rum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutiones ſunt in gloſsis. et in Intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe de quo. i.</note> Seinge then that it is vſurye whatſoeuer is deſired and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken aboue the head ſumme, as it is without any doubte; and is alſo ſo taken in all places in the lawes, doeſt thou yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde I ſaye, whether it be ſynne to take any thynge for it? Is not vſurye forbydden harde ynough bothe in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall lawes, and alſo in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porall lawes? Is not this a playne texte of Chriſte whiche I haue nowe certayne tymes aledged out of the ſixt chapter of Luke, where oure ſauioure hymſelfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth ſayeng, ſe that ye lende lokynge for no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyng agayn? nothyng is not ſome thinge, neither is ſome thinge, nothing. What ſayeth the Pſalme? Lorde who ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:10377:42"/> dwell in thy tabernacle? Who ſhall reſt vpon thy holy hyll? Euen he that leadeth an vncor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupt lyfe, and lendeth not hys money vpon vſurye.</p>
               <p>Where ſhall he than become that geueth his money vpon vſury? Euen without the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. In that heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where the deuilles chace one another with do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge forkes.<note place="margin">Exo. xxij.</note> What ſaieth the lorde in the ſeconde boke of Moſes? If thou lende money to any of my people, thou ſhalt not oppreſſe hym with vſury.<note place="margin">Ezech. 18.</note> Item Ezechiel nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth thoſe amonge the righteous that re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue no vſurye,<note place="margin">Leu. xxV</note> nor any thyng ouer. Item in the third booke of moſes. Thou ſhalt not take vſurye of thy brother, nor yet vantage. Thou ſhalt not lende hym thy money vpon vſurye,
<pb facs="tcp:10377:43"/> nor lende hym of thy fode to haue aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage by it, but ſhalt feare thy God. Lo, if thou muſt feare thy God concernyng vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt it nedes be ſynne. Item in the fifth boke of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.<note place="margin">Deu. xxiij</note> Thou ſhalt be no vſurer vnto thy brother, neither in money, nor in fode, nor in any maner of thynge that is lent vpon vſury, that the lord may bleſſe the. That is leaſt he courſe and condempne the yf thou do the contrary.<note place="margin">xiiij q. iiij i.c. et q. § c. quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur. etc. nec hoc d. q. iiij. etex. de Vſuris c. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; ij. &amp; in alijs locis.</note> In lyke maner is vſurye forbidden in the ſpiritual lawes written, ſo that it is not lawfull to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte vſury neither for prieſts nor yet for laye men. And the temporall power ſubmitteth her ſelfe vnto the ſpiritualtie in ſuch caſes as drawe to ſinne and diſquiete the conſcience.
<pb facs="tcp:10377:43"/> Willyng men therein to obeye the ſpiritualtie.<note place="margin">Authen. de Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſt. titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus. Anno <hi>M. D.</hi> &amp; Anno. <hi>M. D.</hi> xxx. auguſte Vind. lico<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum.</note> Whereby ſhe will alſo haue vſurye forboden and abolyſhed. Yea beſydes the holſome lawes &amp; ſtatutes of this realme, the moſte puyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt emperour Charles now reignyng and all the ſtates of thempire together aſſembled at ſundry generall counſailes, haue earneſtly forbidden, abro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gated and beſides that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be of none effecte all maner of contractes agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and bargaynes, myxt with vſury. Lo, doeſt thou yet aſke whether it be ſynne to receyue more then thou haſt le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? Thou heareſt and ſeeſt by many eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and playne textes of holy ſcripture, and by many places alledged out of the lawes, that it is againſt God and the hyer
<pb facs="tcp:10377:44"/> powers both ſpiritual and tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porall, thinkeſt thou then that if ſuche vſurers as haue taken ſo muche vſurye of many one, were depriued of their head money, were ſerued amiſſe? And that it were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, that whoſoeuer had geuen ſo muche vſurye as the head ſom me amounteth, ſhould neither geue any more vſurye nor yet returne the head ſumme? For vſurye is forbidden, &amp; the vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers haue had warning ynou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gh. And yf nowe the hyer po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers and magiſtrates would earneſtly and openly proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me al maner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tractes mixt with vſurye to be voyde and of none effecte, and to put in execution the forſayd ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces contayned in Goddes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and the holſome lawes and
<pb facs="tcp:10377:44"/> ſtatutes of this realme agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ſame, thynkeſt thou that it were not well done? Haue not thoſe helhundes had warnyng ynough? Haue they not bene ſufficiently admony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, both by open textes of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſcripture, and alſo by holſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me lawes and ſtatutes before mencioned?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſhe Paſquill, thou art to tediouſe for me, I can holde my peace no longer. I haue herkened vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> till I ſweate agayne. Thou haſt tolde me ſo muche, that I muſte nedes graunte that it were better &amp; more godly, if one would lende to another for nought, then for money, neither can I chuſe, but muſt nedes confeſſe that it is ſynne alſo, yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take more
<pb facs="tcp:10377:45"/> than he dyd lende, for both the ſpirituall and temporall lawe ſayth that it is vſurye, howe littell or whatſoeuer it be, and agayne the holy ſcripture and our Lord and ſauiour Chriſte hymſelfe, and beſydes this the ſpirituall and temporall magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates do forbidde vſury. If ſo be then that God doth cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te it for greate ſynne whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is committed againſte the commaundementes and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces of the hyer powers onely, howe muche more wyll he counte it ſynne, and greuou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſly punyſhe whatſoeuer is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt his diuine maie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtie his onely begotten ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, his worde, and agaynſt the hyer powers both ſpirituall and temporall alſo? Therfore muſt vſurye nedes
<pb facs="tcp:10377:45"/> be a greate ſynne doubtles. But yet there are certayne ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the lawes, wherin a man may take ſomewhat more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath lent? Wherfore I bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, that in this lendynge wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of thou ſpeakeſt are many ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and exceptions wherein it is no ſynne at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>In dede, there are certayne caſes, wherein the ſurplus is not taken for vſurye,<note place="margin">Gloſs. in c. quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multi. xiiij q. iiij.</note> as where the ſurplus is taken for auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of dammage, for there it is counted and taken for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and not for vſurye.<note place="margin">What vſurp is</note> For vſurye is, when any thynge is taken aboue the head ſumme, the creditour remayning har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meles, &amp; the head ſumme not beinge diminiſhed. But this is not vſurye, when a thynge is
<pb facs="tcp:10377:46"/> taken away from the one ende and put to agayne to the other ende, as I wil declare vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Foraſmuche as thou haſt brought me into this diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, I can not yet ceaſſe from it. Thou ſpeakeſt here of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, I pray the tell me, is not Intereſt vſury, ſurplus and ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che other all one? Or what dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ference is there among them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>(aduaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tage)</hi> Cum per id proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r dom. et poſſeſs. l. ij. C. de arg. et ret. poſſeſs.</note>Well, ſeynge thou art diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I take it alſo for a paſtime, and wyll gladly talke with the further in the matter. But of Intereſt wyll I tell the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes. It is farre another maner of thynge then vſurye, although it be a couerynge for muche vſury. I wyll fyrſt anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were
<pb facs="tcp:10377:46"/> the to thy thirde queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Cum quis que ſue rei moderator &amp; arbiter ſit. l. In re mandata, c mandat i. <hi>(Loſſe &amp;) hinderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce.</hi>
                  </note> whiche thou mouedeſt before, namely whether it be not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for a man to occupie and vſe his goodes as he maye beſt for his aduauntage, for thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt elles buylde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it againe.<note place="margin">Arg. l. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticia § Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ris precep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta, ff. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtit. &amp; iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. &amp; ſic ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cundum. l. Nam hoc natura. ff. de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dict. indeb. l. Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re naturae. ff. de reg. Iur.</note> Wherefore thou ſhalt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande that the temporall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers and their lawes do not forbydde the the vſe of thy goo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des accordynge to thy wyll &amp; pleaſure for thy moſt profite &amp; aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage. Notwithſtanding although the ſame power in ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerall wyll and graunteth the the vſe of it after thy mynde without any mans loſſe or hyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deraunce, for thy moſte profite and aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, yet doth it not extende ſo farre and ſo ſtraigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely againſt thy queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the holy ſcripture doth. Howebeit
<pb facs="tcp:10377:47"/> the temporall power dothe ſo <note n="a" place="margin">L. ſi quis §. fin ff. de Inſtito. act l. ſi pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pilli. §. ſed &amp; ſi quis ff. de nego geſt d. ll. nam hoc. nat. &amp; iure. naturae.</note> ſtraightely and narrowely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehende the vſe of thy goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that thou canſt not buylde vſury vpon this queſtion. For neither the ſpirituall nor tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral powers do permitte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the the vſe of thy goodes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further, then as farre as it is not agaynſt God and his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes. If ſo be then that they forbidde the the vſe of them.<note n="b" place="margin">arg ab of ficio Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratus et poſſint adduci in numerabi lia exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla exutro que iure.</note> as it is againſt God and his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do they alſo forbidde the the ſame in vſury. For that is againſt God and the lawes as thou haſt hearde before.</p>
               <p>But yet the holy ſcripture go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth further, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehendeth the vſe of them more ſtraitely. For the hier powers ſuffre the to applye the vſe of them for thy moſte profite and aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb facs="tcp:10377:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo that thou do not hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der nor harme any man wyth them, nor attempte any forbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thynge therere with. But the holy ſcripture wadeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and wyll alſo that thou ſhalt do good with them. The temporall powers in generall are content with the although thou do no good with them, ſo that thou do no hurte or harm with them. But the holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture taketh better holde of thyne aucthoritie whiche thou wylt haue in thy goodes.<note place="margin">As hath ben decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue.</note> And wyll that thou ſhalt not onely do no harme with them but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo that thou ſhalt and muſt do good with them, yf ſo be that thou wilt be a Chriſtian, &amp; the chylde of God, and not a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyme or a Turke. Thou arte forbydden to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitte any vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
<pb facs="tcp:10377:48"/> with them, and thou arte commaunded to ſerue and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coure thy neyghboure wyth them, as thou haſt hearde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Therefore ſhalt thou vnderſtande and take this aunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were concernynge thy thyrde queſtion, that it is not lawfull for the without any difference to occupie and vſe thy goodes at thyne owne pleaſure, as thou canſt beſt, for if thou woul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt occupye and vſe them in matters contrary to God and his lawes, thou haſt none auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torite to do it, for thou art for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden ſo to do bothe by God &amp; alſo by the hye powers who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou muſt obeye, or elles thou art the childe of the deuel both body and ſoule, for God is thy creatour,<note place="margin">Rom. xiij.</note> and the hyer power is thy defender vnder God.<note place="margin">Gen. i.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Of a truthe Paſquill this ſame is a good Inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I thinke that any man can reproue it. And I aſſure the that I haue oftentymes hearde this obiection, that a man is lord and maiſter of his owne goodes and hath aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite to vſe them for his commo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dite and profite, thinking ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by to make vſury lawfull, or at leaſt that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de his goodes for nought. But nowe I perceyue ryght wel that a man not onely hath none auctorite to vſe his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in vſurye or in any other thinge agaynſt God and the lawes, but alſo that he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of very dutye to ſerue other with it for nought, accordynge to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manifeſt inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche
<pb facs="tcp:10377:49"/> thou haſt geuen me out of the holy ſcripture. But I pray the nowe tell me ſome, what of the Intereſt, for there will alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall ſome queſtions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Truely of this Intereſt hath Doctor Martyne Luther ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ſufficient inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his boke by the before mencio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, wherewith thou oughteſt (yf thou were not ſo ful of hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des flyes) to be ſatiſfyed. But to thintent thou mayeſt haue occaſion to demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de more que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtions, I will repete it agayne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. Det. in l. Vnica <hi>C.</hi> deſen<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pro eo quod int. prof.</note>This worde Intereſt hath many ſignifications amonge the lawyers: But they ſerue not al for our purpoſe, wherfor I ſpeake of that, whereof thou demaundeſt.</p>
               <p>And the ſame is nothynge
<pb facs="tcp:10377:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> elles but amendes making for the loſſe and hinderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which the creditour maye haue ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſon of the debters none payment at his daye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. And this is called ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gantly of doctor Martine Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, a ſcathe watche, for it is nothynge elles. And yf there be no ſcathe wache (that is, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table loſſe or damage ſuſtained by the creditour) there can be no Intereſt, but it turneth to vſury whatſoeuer is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the head ſumme.</p>
               <p>This loſſe or dammage may happen to a man two maner of wayes.<note place="margin">quo ad no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrum pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſitum. ut. ſup.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt if thou lende me twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty poundes, and I promiſe the to repaye the ſame at a certayn daye and place apointed. The daye beyng expired. I breake
<pb facs="tcp:10377:50"/> promiſe with the. By the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof thy creditours op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſe the, and put the to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and loſſe. And if I had kept promiſe with the thou ſhuldeſt not haue neded to ſuffre any dammage, but myghteſt haue pleaſed thy creditour without any further coſtes &amp; charges.</p>
               <p>Secondely, when I haue lent the my money, and thou hauynge promiſed and appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted me a daye of payment, fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt in thy promyſe and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thyne appointement with me, I may chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vpon a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, by the whiche I myght haue gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſomewhat toward my lyuynge, but thou by the promyſe breakynge cauſeſt me to loſe the bargaine, and ſo hin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dereſt me in myne occupienge, and liuinge.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:50"/>
               <p>Lo here are twoo maner of loſſes. Wherefore the Intereſt is elegantly called amonge the lawyers a waſſhinge of ſcate, or an hyndering and ceaſſinge of gaynes.<note place="margin">Gloſ. in Ver. Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibile, ibi Det. &amp; com. d. l. Vnica. d. tit.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Nowe this loſſe or ſcathe maye happen vnto a man two maner of wayes as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerninge the time or day apointed. Firſt when I do not kepe promyſe with the, as it is ſayde before. Secondely alſo before my day is expyred. For it may chaunce that thy creditour may arreſte the and put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to hynderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, before my dayes come and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aduenture before thou waſt ware of hym. Or thou mayeſt chaunce vpon a bargayne, in the meane ſeaſon wherby thou mighteſt do good, but forſomu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che as I haue thy money in
<pb facs="tcp:10377:51"/> hande, hauyng apoicnted the a daye of payment, whiche is not yet come, thou muſt forgo the ſayde bargayne. Thus I ſaye maye this loſſe or ſcathe chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce two maner of wayes, that is to ſaye, before, or after the time apointed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Well go to then, what ſayeſt thou to the fyrſt waye, when the loſſe chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth after the day apointed? That is, when thou by thy breakynge of promyſe with me, cauſeſt me to incurre into loſſe and dammage?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Truely thys requireth no greate diſputacion,<note n="a" place="margin">Natura n. aequum eſt ut be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefacia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th. in l. Ex hoc iure. ff. de iuſt. &amp; iur. In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtituti ſte in tt. de ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligat. Vbi de oblig. ad. an thi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toradi.</note> for if ſo bee that thou haſt layde out for me and lent me thy money at my nede, and haſt gentely and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly
<pb facs="tcp:10377:51"/> ſerued and ſuccoured me with it, the lawe of nature and alſo the lawes written graunte no leſſe than that I muſt be .a. thankefull vnto the, and as muche as lyeth in me, kepe &amp; ſaue the harmeles ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this repugnaunt to the lawe of God, for God wyll not that I ſhal be vnthankeful nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther wyll he that I ſhall enda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage any man. Howbeit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>(Harme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les)</hi> Siue ſtipu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latus ſint Siue non. per Iura uulg. d. dam. etc.</note> yet were it good and Godly, that euery creditour and debtoure as then woulde haue reſpecte to the qualite of the perſone, of the tyme, and of the matter, &amp; temper it after ſuche ſorte, as it might be conformable to the Chriſtian loue. Many thinges myght be here inferred and diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>puted concernynge the ſame, but the caſes and qualities of
<pb facs="tcp:10377:52"/> all circumſtaunces are diuers, and in, or by one man otherwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe then in or by another.<note place="margin">Luc. Vi.</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the concience muſt partely be charged, with Chriſtian cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite, and with theſe wordes of Chriſte, whatſoeuer ye would that other men ſhoulde do to you, do ye eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: by theſe thynges ought the matter to be iudged and deter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mined.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>It muſt nedes be good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that thou ſhouldeſt thanke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully contente me. But I muſt tell the this alſo, yf I were ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che and thou pore, and that thy wyll were good, but thou we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt not able to paye me, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witſtandynge that thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not bene ſlacke to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb facs="tcp:10377:52"/> thy ſelfe with all diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce poſſible for to come oute of my debte, not hauing leawde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor waſtfully conſumed nor ſpent thy ſubſtaunce, or if thou haddeſt had ſome miſchaunce, whiche were no greate loſſe &amp; hynderaunce vnto me, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the a great deale, forſomuch as I were more able to beare it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou, here thynkeſt thou that I ought to haue reſpecte to the condicion and qualitie of the matter, &amp; vſe it accordinge to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to extremite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Yea forſothe, thynke I in dede, all men knowledge and graunte it to be good reaſon, yea &amp; it is but reaſon in dede, that thou ſhuldeſt be kept har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meles, and be recompenced for
<pb facs="tcp:10377:53"/> thy loſſe and hynderaunce,<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>D.</hi> c. Luc. Vi. Math. <hi>5.</hi> c Cum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes de Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitut. Ex l. i. ff. quod quiſ que uiris. etc.</p>
                     <p>i. Pet. iiij. Matth. <hi>V</hi> Eccli. c. xxix. Pulcherri me de hac noſtra ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teria.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>For no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged nor occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue in vngodly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> but whatſoeuer thou doeſt thy ſelf thou doeſt it to the lorde. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ought to vſe hymſelfe in all thinges, as he woulde be vſed hym ſelfe. Euery man ought to ſhewe loue and amite to his neighbour, &amp; to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful when neceſſite requireth. But this I ſaye agayne, if ſo be, that I had layed oute and lent my money to a man gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and louingly, for his commo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dite and profite at his nede, &amp; he were afterwarde ſlouthfull and ſlacke or ydell, or a Ryo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, a dronkarde, and horemon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, a player, or ſuche lyke, and by his owne wyl or at the leaſt thorough his owne negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſhoulde put me to loſſe and hynderaunce, wyth ſuche a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not beare, but muſt nedes
<pb facs="tcp:10377:53"/> go agaynſt hym,<note place="margin">Vide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach. xij.</note> tyll he ſtynke agayne. And I truſt that in ſo doynge, I ſhoulde do well and Godly. But in neceſſite and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nocencie, let a Chriſten man, be a Chriſten man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>But what ſayeſt thou of the ſeconde waye after the daye of payment be expired? That is to ſaye, when thou hyndereſt me of ſome good bargayne by the reaſon of thy promyſe brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kinge and none payment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Here muſt I nedes make a diſtinction: Or els thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſome fynde an hole to flye out at. And I ſaye that he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom thou haſt gently lent thy money vpon his promyſe doth not well to hynder the of
<pb facs="tcp:10377:54"/> thy lyuinge. For if he do he is worthy to receyue punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for hys ingratitude, and to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke the ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. But adde, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil niſi quod in veritate inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, no more than thou haſt loſt by it in dede. Therfore I ſay? muſt a diſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be made and as here Doctor Martyne Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſayeth alſo, a concionable reſpecte and remembraunce muſt be had, whether, and if ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che a bargayne dyd chaunce in dede, whether thou alſo mygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt haue had the ſame bargain in caſe thou haddeſt had thy money. And whether it was ſuche a bargayne in dede as myght haue bene lawfully con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tracted whereunto belongeth many thynges, whether it had bene profitable for the or not. Item wether thou couldeſt
<pb facs="tcp:10377:54"/> not haue forborne thy money for it, theſe and ſuche lyke cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtaunces ought to be pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and remembred leaſt thou deſire or take any more then thou haſt ſuffered loſſe in dede, or elles it is no Intereſt, but theft and vſurye. For vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this pretence thou robbeſt thy pore brother. Therefore oughteſt thou not onely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre all theſe thynges, but alſo to haue reſpecte to the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicion and qualite of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of the tyme, and of the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, as it is mencioned aboue in the fyrſt waye. Whether the debter was able to do it, and to paye the, whether he haue wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully neglected it or not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he haue ſuffered any loſſe or miſfortune, whether thou haſt more loſſe be it then he or
<pb facs="tcp:10377:55"/> not or whether he haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any loſſe or miſfortune, whether thou haſt more loſſe be it then he or not, or whether thou haue littell hynderaunce by it and he a greate deale, or not, whether thou myghteſt as ſoone haue looſt by the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as haue gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thing by it, whether thou myghteſt haue bought the ſame bargain with a cleare conſcience, and with honeſte, and ſumma thou oughteſt ſo to ſtudie &amp; to waye the matter, that thou become not a thefe &amp; an vſurer. That thou mayeſt ſo deale with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as thou wouldeſt be dealt wyth all. That thou meaſure not to ſharpe, to thintent thou mayeſt obtayne agayne a full,<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>V</hi> Eccli. xij.</note> ſhaken and heaped meaſure in to thy boſome. And that thou
<pb facs="tcp:10377:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> mayeſt againe in tyme of nede obtaine mercy and become not an vnmercifull, falſe, deceitfull Turke, Panyme and Iewe, to thy Chriſten brother.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Of a truthe Paſquill thou concludeſt very narrowely.</p>
               <p>Howe beit, in dede I can fynde no greate faute with it yf ſo be that I wylbe a Chrſtian, But yf I wylbe an vſurer, a lyar, &amp; a thefe, then haue I nothynge to do with all this buſynes. I paſſe not of it, but let it go, whatſouer I gette I haue it, whatſoeuer or whatſoeuer I am called, yf I maye gette it I take it. But if I wil be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian (I ſaye) ſurely then I can not correcte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in thy ſaienges. For yf ſo be that I do not ſo pondre and waighe the loſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:10377:56"/> but require and take it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any conſideracion of al the circumſtaunces, it can not fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, but I muſt nedes (as it is ſayde before) become a thefe &amp; an vſurer, robbyng my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by lyenge and deceiuing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neither ſhal ignoraunce excuſe me in this matter, though I ſaye for mine excuſe that I did it not wyttyngly but againſte my wyll, for I myght take bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hede, and if I had ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and remembred it with as muche diligence as I ought to haue done, and as tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet had put hym to ouermuche wrong without my wil &amp; knowledge, it might be ſaide, tranſeat cum ceteris erroribus. And I muſt committe the matter to God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Yea that muſt do as well as
<pb facs="tcp:10377:56" rendition="simple:additions"/> it maye. But yet there maye be no knauerye hid vnder the fame knowynge &amp; willing. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Well go to, tell me nowe of the loſſe ſuſtayned by the credi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour before the daie of paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. As when my creditours trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me before the daye be come whiche thou haſt appoincted me that I ſhoulde be payde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Here muſt I make another diſtinction. If ſo be that thou haue layed out thy money for me at my nede, and haſt decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto me what feare &amp; care thou tokeſt for thy creditours wherupon I haue promiſed to ſaue the harmeles, or to tourne vnto the thy money agayne, why ſhoulde I not be bounde
<pb facs="tcp:10377:57"/> to do it? For beſydes this that reaſon doth require it, I haue alſo made the promiſe to do it, by the onely reaſon wherof he were ſufficiently obliged.<note place="margin">Vt ſupra.</note> And here doth the Lawe of God &amp; alſo the lawe of man graunte the no leſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thou ough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt to be ſaued harmeles, only adde to this, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame that thou oughteſt to adde in the firſt waye after the daye of pai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, thus doynge thou ſhalt not onely do no wronge, but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo deale vprightely and Godly</p>
               <p>But if ſo be, that I haue pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed the nothinge but onely for lacke of payment at my day and terme apointed forſomuch as thou waſt not ware of this trouble, what wilt thou then gette of me by the lawe? For I haue promiſed the nothynge,
<pb facs="tcp:10377:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> neither diddeſt thou motione any ſuche thynges vnto me, nor caſt any ſuch doubtes, alſo thou myghteſt haue beſtowed thy money aboute ſome other thynges whereof thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt haue none aſſuraunce to be profitable vnto the or not. Yea thy money might alſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue tourned the to loſſe that no man had knowen of it. What can I do with thy miſfortune? I myght alſo paradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue founde ſome other frende that woulde haue lent me ſo muche without any ſuche bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynes. Therfore after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremite of the lawe, I owe the nought. But after the lawe of nature I am bounde to rendre the thankes, wherfore I thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it good reaſon that I do hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe the to beare thy loſſe. For
<pb facs="tcp:10377:58"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10377:58"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10377:59"/> thou mighteſt haue kept thi mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney in thy coffre, or mighteſt haue done good with it ſome other wayes, and haue abyden the auenture as wel of fortune as of miſfortune. Seyng then that thou haſt gentely lent me thy money and holpen me out of my nedes, I wil not, neither ought I to be ſo vnkynde that I woulde ſuffre the to incurre any loſſe for my ſake, but will rather helpe the agayne and beare parte of loſſes and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with the for ſo would I be dealt withall of other. Howe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit thou maieſt not vſe falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hede with me, and brynge in more loſſe then thou haſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in dede, thou mayeſt not ſo ordre the matter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt go fre thy ſelfe, and laye al the burden vpon my backe, for
<pb facs="tcp:10377:59"/> I will beare with the, and not alone. Forſomuche as I wyll be thankefull and helpe the to beare thy loſſe without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, it ſhall become the in lyke-maner to be thanckfull and not to begyle me, nor to vſe any thefte or vſurye with me. But yf ſo be that I ſhall beare the loſſe alone, then wyll I paye it no more, for thou maieſt not lawfully with one ſyſter make two brethren in lawe. &amp;c. for I haue paide thy loſſe according to thy promyſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>In good fayth Paſquill I muſt nedes alowe thy reaſon, when I pondre and perpende thy ſayenges and meanynge accordyngly. But howe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou by the other waye be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the daye apoincted? As
<pb facs="tcp:10377:60"/> when a bargayne cometh to my handes before thy daye of payment become, whiche bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn I muſt for go becauſe my ready money is out of my han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, in thy handes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Here do I ſaye firſt as I ſayde before. If I haue promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the to ſaue the harmeles, &amp; to beare thy loſſe all the whyle I haue had thy money, then is it reaſon that I make the ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des for ſo muche as thou haſt loſt in dede, but yet thou muſt be ware y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou vſe no deceite, and that thou vſe the ſelfe in al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wayes, as it hath bene ſayde aboue in the other waye, after the daye apointed, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring, perpending and inquiringe all and ſinguler circumſtaunces, condicions and qualities leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:10377:60"/> thou become a thefe or an vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer on my behalfe, and then wil I and alſo ought to ſatiſfie my promyſe and reaſon, and ſaue the harmeles.</p>
               <p>But yf I haue made the no further promyſe then vpon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion, that if I kepe not touch with the, what wilt thou then get of me by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe? For thou waſt agreed with me. But yf thou chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ſuffre any loſſe or dammage by the reaſon of my promyſe breakyng and not kepynge touche with the, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I haue promyſed the or not, I ought muſt and will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidre and eaſe the ſame, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will I owe the no more but lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue and fauoure. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, yf thou wilt conſydre &amp; remembre all circumſtaunces, as hath bene ſayd aboue in the
<pb facs="tcp:10377:61"/> ſeconde waye after the daye apointed, and wilt be no diſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bler, if I do then perceiue, that thou arte hyndered becauſe of my money, I wyll vſe me ſelfe, as I would y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> another ſhoulde vſe hymſelfe towardes me.</p>
               <p>But in any wyſe, become not thou a diſſembler, thefe or vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer on my behalfe. Summa, whenſoeuer any man putteth the to loſſe or hinderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with out thy deſeruynge, thou ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt not, yf thou aſke and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue amendes, neither is that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vſury, but an Intereſt. But whereſoeuer is no leſſe, there is alſo no Intereſt, but it is vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye whatſoeuer is demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded or receiued.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>(Loſſe)</hi> Poſſit ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di. nec pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculum ſed uide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur pro parte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>CC. <hi>c.</hi>
                     </hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uig. de V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuris.</note>Lo this is an Intereſt, as muche as pertayneth to len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge and borrowing. And by
<pb facs="tcp:10377:61"/> this maieſt thou take in all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of lendyng and borrowing a ſufficient inſtruction, to do vpryghtely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>O lorde God, yf all that be vſury, and ſo great ſynne that hath bene taken, and yet dayly is taken otherwyſe, and after another ſorte, then thou haſt nowe declared of the Intereſt frende Paſquill, where ſhall then many an honeſt man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Mary without the doores ſhal they ſtande, as I haue ſaid before, in that heauen, where the blacke men chace one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with dong forkes, yea where a lode of hote burninge coles is worth but one half pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.
<pb facs="tcp:10377:62"/> What wilt thou ſpeake of honeſt men? There is neither honeſtie nor vertue, where as vſury beareth any rule. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement both of God, and alſo of the hyer po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wers is deſpiſed, body &amp; ſoule for wicked Mammo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſake put in ieoperdy, and where oure neighbour is ſpoyled and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of his ſweate and blowde, what wilt thou there ſpeake of honeſtie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Well Paſquil it is an heauy matter God wote, as thou ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeſt. Trueth it is that thou haſt layde ſuche a ſure founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ouerthrowe it, notwithſtanding I muſt yet aſke ſomewhat more. It ſo be that I lende a man money, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne otherwiſe but for nought, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10377:62"/> vpon this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicion that he ſhal ſaue me harmeles, and yf he do preſente me with ſome preſent or gifte, might I not receyue it with honeſtie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Lo, whence commeſt thou with that? Hath not Doctor Luther geuen the a ſufficient reaſon therof? If any man ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the ought, why ſhoulde it not be lawfull for the to receiue the ſame ſhameles and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les? But what calleſt thou a gyft or a preſent?<note place="margin">I: donari ff. de Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nationib. <hi>A.</hi> xx. in Sua Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. eo. t. etc.</note> A gyft or a preſent is that whiche is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frely without compulſion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedynge of a thankefull harte, or of ſome other good inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and fauourable diſpoſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Not that any man muſt geue the ſomewhat if he wyll haue thy money, and that thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:10377:63"/> no money to helpe thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour withall, oneles thou fele hym with ſome preſent or gift, nor yet this, whan I ſaye, yf thou wilt geue me a couple of crownes, or if thou wilt geue my wyfe or my chyldren thys or that, to drinke, I wil ſe what I can do.<note place="margin">Nullo mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cogent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ut dicit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari ff de Reg. Iur.</note> But it muſt procede of a fre wyll without any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner compulſion, or elles ſuche gift and preſent whereof thou ſpeakeſt is no gift, but playne vſury, and maketh the a thefe, and an vſurer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Paſquill thou wylt not lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue. But what and if I do a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great pleaſure and high ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce with it, &amp; he doth alſo take it for no leſſe, &amp; woulde not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke twyſe or thryſe ſo muche as he geueth me that he woulde
<pb facs="tcp:10377:63"/> forbeare the money,<note place="margin">dec. ſcien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti. de reg. Iur. ut in.</note> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth &amp; praieth me howe can I be againſt that thynge whiche he doeth with his good will?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſingeſt ſtil thyne olde ſonge. Doctor Luther hath ſufficiently tolde the all theſe thynges, what ſpeakeſt thou of hygh ſeruice, and his good will? If nede did not preſſe him, he woulde deſyre none of thy hinnes nor yet of thy geſe. Neither would he geue the ſo muche as the tayle of a peare, nor yet begge of the ſo muche as a littell pece of breade. For nede maketh an olde horſe to tratte. Whatſoeuer a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt nedes do, can not be done by his good wyll. Therfore ceaſſe to ſpeake of good wyll har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:64"/>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>It is true indede Paſquill, many one geueth oftentymes great giftes to another to thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tente he myght obtayne ſome money lent of hym, which if he had no nede of hym would not geue him one halfpeny for god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſake, in hys mooſte miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. Wherfore I may ceaſe to ſpeake of God wyll for it is a nedy wyll.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, verely, as pertaynyng to hym that giueth the gifte, it is a nede will, and no free will. But as touching hym that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyueth the gyfte, it is vſurye and robberye. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding yf any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue me ought of thankefulnes, or otherwiſe: of frendſhipp, whether it were before the lendynge or after. I
<pb facs="tcp:10377:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> would truſt to receiue it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: but I muſt beware that I haue no diſſembler nor vſurer in my herte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt handle the better yet or I go, Paſquill. What and if I be an occupier, and haue not ſo muche money but I coulde occupie it all my ſelfe in myne owne ſcience and gette ſome what by it. Notwithſtanding a good fellowe being in neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te praieth me to lende hym .xl. or .l. crownes, whom I would be loth to leaue in nede, and yet if I ſhould lende hym I ſhould hinder myne owne occupieng. Might I not lawfully &amp; with honeſtie take here fyue or ſyxe in the hundred for amendes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:65"/>
               <p>Ah Syr, here muſt I nedes arreſte &amp; ſtande a while. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I praye the geue eare to that whiche I ſhal ſpeake. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke as the Cuckowe bewraieth hym ſelfe and crieth ſorth hys owne name, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo doeſt thou. For the Cuckowe cryeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge but Cuckowe, and that is his name. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo crieſt thou all into my bagge, neuer full, neuer full, and that is thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Thou wilt be very merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and iuſt, and wouldeſt be loth to leaue thy neighbour in neceſſite, &amp; ſpecially thy frende and fellowe, whiche is a good waye to begynne: But that fearefull crye which foloweth, ſoundinge on this wyſe, it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth me, I muſt die for hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger yf the bagge be not ſoone full, is the deuill, and ſuffereth
<pb facs="tcp:10377:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> the not to performe thy good enterpriſe. I haue ſufficiently declared vnto the out of the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſcripture, aboue where this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is alſo, in a maner, that thou arte bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to do vnto thy neighbour as thou wouldeſt be done to, in lendynge in hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge and in counſaylynge. And thou graunteſt thy ſelfe, that it is no reaſon, that thou ſhouldeſt leaue thy frende or neighbour in daunger. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yf thou haue it,<note place="margin">Vt ſupra clare.</note> and doeſt it not, then art thou an vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Turke, and doeſt againſt God, againſt chriſtian charite,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>(Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible)</hi> Dec. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo poteſt de Reg. Jur. inui l. impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bil. ff. cod tit.</note> and againſt thyne owne conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience. But if thou haue it not, and arte not able to do it, then doth neither God nor yet the worlde compel the to it, For to thynges impoſſible is no man
<pb facs="tcp:10377:66"/> bounde. Paraduenture thou wilt ſaye, I haue it well, and coulde alſo do it (thanked bee God) but not without my hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deraunce, for I haue nede of it my ſelfe. Alas good Neuerful, canſt thou do it, and canſt alſo not do it? If ſo muche loſſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue thereof vnto the, becauſe that paraduenture thyne occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pienge is but ſlender, and may not beare the lacke of ſo muche money without the hurte of thyne occupienge and liuinge, why ſaieſt thou then that thou canſt not do it? For thou ough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt to ſaye I woulde be gladly do it, but I am nedy my ſelfe, I muſt kepe my wyfe and chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and prouide for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fode and other neceſſaryes as the Lorde hath commaunded me, wherfore I can not do it. If it
<pb facs="tcp:10377:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> be ſo that one muſt nedes ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre penury,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In this caſis.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>asnon ſint diſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine. i. Iohn. iij. Eccl. xxix et ſup. ſatis.</note> let hym ſuffre it vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to whome God hath ſent it. Trueth it is that one Chriſten man is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to helpe another bothe with his body and goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, howe be it the neceſſite is not here ſo greate. Beſides this, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce brought thy ſelf into the breers, ſo that it is thine owne doinge. Thou mighteſt haue occupied a whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le by the hundred wel ynough vntill the thouſande had bene growen. But thou wouldeſt haue fyue corners of the ſacke, where thou myghteſt fulwell haue bene content with foure, as other do is ones. Wherfore if thy Creditour haue truſted the with muche and that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough couetouſnes, and beſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that paraduenture hath
<pb facs="tcp:10377:67"/> deliuered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naughty olde, rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and deceyuable wares, &amp; peraduenture alſo to dere, let him care howe he may be paid of the. And let hym take this for his puniſhement, that thou art not able nowe to paye him. If any man haue hindered the with his naughty and enhau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced wares, let hym take parte with the, and receyue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his deſeruing. If ſome vſurer haue ſucte the vp, then hath he already all that thou waſt able to do, wherefore he maye take his amendes in his owne handes. Thou wilt ſaye I am be giled enhau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, or eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp with vſury, and yet muſt I beare the burthen, for he wilbe payde, and putteth me to trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble &amp; loſſe. Haſt thou not heard what I haue tolde the? If ſo
<pb facs="tcp:10377:67"/> be (I ſaye) that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt brought the ſelfe into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breers through thyne owne couetouſnes, or by negligence, ſlouthfulnes, rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge or playenge, then arte thou ſerued wel ynough, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge to thy deſeruyng. Why dydeſt thou not occupie after thyne habilite? If thou ſeeſt that it is to dere for the, &amp; that the vſury putteth the to hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deraunce, why doeſt thou not ordre thy ſelf therafter? Thou wilt ſaye, I would fayne gette ſomewhat as well as other, &amp; would faine alſo go with other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alas good fellowe, runne thou with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as farre as thou canſt. But I would rather go faire &amp; ſoftely, thynkynge that of ſufferaunce commeth eaſe. What profite is it for the, to get a quarter of meale whiche
<pb facs="tcp:10377:68"/> perchaunce will yelde the .xxx or .xl. fayre houſholde loues when ſcant one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is thyne owne? And the reſt belonging to thy creditours or le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, to thy deſtroyers and robbers the vſurers? Should I nowe abate my lyuinge for thy ſake? Truely I can not do it. But if ſo be, that thou haſt had any miſchaunce without thy deſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge, ſhewe it vnto the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer thou arte ſued, and let thoſe ryche Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes haue pacience with the, it can leſſe hurte them then the. Lo thus myght a man knowe that thou canſt not do it, and nedeſt not to ſay that thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt do it wel ynough, but not with out thyne hynderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſaye, if thou canſt not do it why ſayeſt thou then that
<pb facs="tcp:10377:68"/> thou canſt do it? And agayne, if thou canſt do it, why ſayeſt thou then that thou canſt not do it? If thyne occupienge be ſo greate that thyne gaynes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue neuertheles after a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable faſhion, although thou ſhuldeſt kepe backe from it .xx. or .xxx. poundes, why art thou then ſuch an helles mouth and neuer full, that thou wilt not helpe thy frende or neyghbour with all. Howe knoweſt thou whether they woulde haue tourned the to good lucke or to loſſe though thou haddeſt beſtowed them? Howe can tell whether God will not proſper the ſo muche the better with the reſte? For he will leaue no good dede vnrewarded. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me peraduenture wyll ſaye, I haue holpen, counſaylled and
<pb facs="tcp:10377:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10377:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10377:70"/> geuen many a good fellowe, &amp; I am neuer the rycher for it.<note place="margin">Prou. xxi</note> But howe knoweſt thou what thou ſhouldeſt be yf thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not done it?<note place="margin">Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſtoppeth his eare at the cri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng of the poore he ſhal crye hymſelfe and not be heard.</note> Thou mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt as ſoone haue fallen in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, as continued in thyne eſtate. Wilt thou make God a lyar? Hath not he ſayde that he will not leaue a draught of colde water vnrewarded? Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue ſurely that if thou lende thy neighbour the odde of .xx. poundes or whatſoeuer it be that thou maieſt forbeare with out loſſe and hynderaunce of thy neceſſary lyuinge,<note place="margin">quimiſere tur paupe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ri fenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur dno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> God wil not leaue it vnrewarded, and thou ſhalt proſper ſo much the better with the reſt, yea thou ſhalt gette more at the lordes hande by lendynge vpon vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnto hym after this ſorte,
<pb facs="tcp:10377:70"/> then by beſtowynge foure ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes as much more in any kind of marchaundiſe.<note place="margin">Prou. xix</note> For it is writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten, he that hath pitie vpon the pore, lendeth vpon vſury vnto the lorde: And looke what he layeth out it ſhalbe payde hym agayne. What knoweſt thou whence proſperite commeth or aduerſite? Or wherefore the one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth and not the other? Therefore I ſaye, why ſayeſt thou that thou canſt do it and yet canſt not do it? If thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not do it, as hath bene ſayde, why doeſt thou ſaye it then? yf thou canſt do it, as nowe hath bene ſayde, why doeſt thou the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denye it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>In dede Paſquill, it is true, as thou ſayeſt. No man kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth wherfore he hath proſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite
<pb facs="tcp:10377:71"/> or aduerſite. If a man be not able to lende, then he can not do it: But yf he maye do it without any ſpecial loſſe or hin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I beleue that he doth to hym ſelfe more hurte then good. For as thou haſt ſayde, God wyll not leaue any good dede vnrewarded, nor any wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked dede vnpunyſhed, neyther doth any man knowe, whence proſperite or aduerſite happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto hym in hys occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienge. Although I thynke in my minde that I maye gayne, and alſo do gayn a great deale with the ouerplus of my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, yet do not I knowe what lucke or proſperite I might ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue had, yf I had lent it to yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der nedy perſone. And where as ſome wil ſaye, I had rather a lyttel birde in my hande the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10377:71"/> a greate many flyenge in the woodes: This is an heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhe ſayenge, for there God is not truſted, but made a lyar, wherfore a chriſten man ought to be aſhamed of ſuche commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicacions. Yea and I thynke it mete alſo and good reaſon, to take hede vnto whome we lende and truſte, what nede he hath, whence it procedeth, and that a yonge beginner occupye wyſely and circumſpectely, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll he be better at eaſe: And that he do rather ſeke to gette a pece of breade for hym ſelfe, then a great deale for another, that kenneth hym no thanke for it, and ſuffereth hym to ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke greate care ſorowe and pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes for it. But yet I muſt aſke one thynge more.</p>
               <p>If I were a great occupier,
<pb facs="tcp:10377:72"/> or els ſome ryche man, hauing muche ruſty money lyenge by me: And a good fellowe came to me, and ſayde I praye the lende me .xl. markes, or a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn ſumme of money, I may haue a bargayne, whereby I maye gette thus muche or ſo muche. Or I put caſe, that he maye gette thryſe as much by it, as geueth me, thynkeſt thou that I might not alſo lawfully take a reaſonable rewarde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>He muſt I aſke the another queſtion, it is not vnknowen to all occupiers, howe vnſtable and vncertayne the trades of byenge and ſellyng are for the moſte parte in ſo muche that a man may ſo ſone miſſe as hitte, and maye as ſone loſe by a bar game as gette by it. Yea there
<pb facs="tcp:10377:72"/> may ſone happen a miſchaunce or ſome other caſualtie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, that a man maye as ſoone get the ſcratchinge behynde hys eare, as the ryngynge in hys purſe. Wherfore I ſay, if thou haddeſt lent a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome money in ſuche wyſe as thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, and he ſhould gette ſome miſchaunce, that his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res did peryſhe, or that his mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney were ſtolen, &amp; that he were robbed, or that the price of that wares dyd fall, or were enda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged ſome other waye ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge loſſe either in the head ſumme, or elles in his gaynes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wouldeſt thou then beare any loſſe with hym? wouldeſt thou be content then to abate ſome thynge of thy head money, or elles of thy lucre?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:73"/>
               <p>No mary I, who woulde counſayll me that? He came to me, and prayed me, &amp; beſydes this he him ſelfe offered me ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che gaynes without any aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge, ſo that I haue lent him my money at his owne requeſt and deſyre, without any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion or conſtraining: Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore then ſhoulde I ſuffre any abatement of my money, ſeyng I myght haue kept it when I had it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Lo there arte thou caught in thyne owne ſnare, as tricke as can be poſſible. If the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney be lent which thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered to a good fellowe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce commeth then the odde mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or gaines? I am ſure thou haſt hearde aboue ſufficiently what lendinge is, and Doctor
<pb facs="tcp:10377:73" rendition="simple:additions"/> Luther hath tolde it the yet more clearer, where he ſayeth: Lending is this, when I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer my money, goodes or ſtuffe to any man, to occupye it as longe as he hath nede of it, or as longe as I can and wyl for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare it, that he maye re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre the ſame to me agayne in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as good as I lent it hym, euen as one neighbour le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to another, diſſhes pottes, pan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, beddinges, clothes, and in lyke maner money, or money worth. Hec ille. Nowe if it be lent, or called lendyng, whence commeth then this vſurye? For whatſoeuer is taken more is called vſury in al the lawes. If ſo bee that thou takeſt any thynge for it, then is it not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led lendyng, but lettinge, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can it be no lendyng. Alſo
<pb facs="tcp:10377:74"/> thou doeſt it not for to ſuccour or to profite hym by thy len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but thou doeſt it for thine owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modite, for thyne own lukers ſake, for els y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wouldeſt let hym go by well ynough.</p>
               <p>Nowe if it be no lendynge, as in dede it can not be, forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as lendynge is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian dede of charitie, but this is a deade of auarice, what ſhoulde it be then? Shoulde it be called occupienge? or bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayninge? yea forſothe. What haſt thou then layde in with hym, thou thy money and he his labour vpon this condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the gaynes or loſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge of the ſame ſhalbe equal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly diuided betwene you, or is there any certayne gaines and loſſe named &amp; agreed betwene you? No. We be agreed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a
<pb facs="tcp:10377:74"/> certayne gaynes, and that I ſhall haue my head money a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine whole and ſounde, &amp; not vpon any loſſe. Whether he do wynne or loſe, I wyll haue my gaynes vndminyſhed, and alſo my head money agayne whole and ſounde. Sayeſt thou ſo? tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> art thou in the right way,<note place="margin">Ironice.</note> and here doth it appeare what thou arte. This is euen the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of all ſtoole robbers. For thou ſitteſt at home behynde the ouen tournyng the apples and peares for burnynge, and thy money is aſſured or pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged (for an vſurer is very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſo neglygent that he wil open his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, except he knowe where to be ſure of his money agayne) So that it is as good as though it laye ſtyll at home in thy cubborde. In ſomuche
<pb facs="tcp:10377:75"/> that neither thou, nor thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ſuſtayneth any loſſe, feare, labour nor paynes. Where as yonder poore ſoule muſt beare ſuffre and take, runnynge, and catchinge, care, paynes, feare, loſſe and ſorrowe. Yea he muſt take more care and thoughte, for thy lukers ſake, &amp; enhau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his wares and deceiue the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple more for thy ſake, then for his owne ſake. If he might ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue his owne gaynes, whereby he myght haue a competent li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, he myght be at reſt, but now muſt he firſt take thought for thy liuinge. And although he ſhould loſe al his owne gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, yet muſt he take thought neuertheles for thyne, for thou wylt in no wyſe lacke it. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he haue had loſſe in his occupienge, yet comeſt thou &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10377:75" rendition="simple:additions"/> wylt haue thy full gaynes and head money. If he haue it not, thou putteſt hym to trouble &amp; hynderaunce. But if he winne and gette by his occupienge, then hath he wonne and gote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it for the, and thou ſpoileſt and robbeſt hym of hys labour, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, feare, ſorowe and ſweate, &amp; yet wylt haue this called len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, and wylt take it with a good conſcience. Should this be called a fellowſhyppe, or bar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayninge? yea it is a rauening and theuyſhe felloweſhippe,<note place="margin">Caſſi. in l. ſinon fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. ff. pro Socio.</note> as the lawes do call it. Therfore can this thy lendyng (if I may ſo calle it) be no more called a felloweſhippe or bargaynyng, that it maye be called lending.</p>
               <p>What is it then? Mary vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry &amp; robbery is it, as thou haſt nowe ſufficiently hearde and
<pb facs="tcp:10377:76"/> as all men perpende and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue ryght well. For thou ſtealeſt and robbeſt him of hys paynefull ſweate and labour, as it hath bene ſayde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Thou wilt haue all thinges ſo plainely and exactely diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that nothynge ſhall eſcape the. But howe thynkeſt thou by this yf I ſhoulde lende my money to a man and ſuffre him to haue the occupienge of it v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this condicion, that if he gotte ought I woulde take parte with hym. If not, I woulde take my heade money agayne, and be content.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Inſtit. de Soci et. § nam et ita</note>Suche Contractes are not reproued in the temporall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, but are left as indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.
<pb facs="tcp:10377:76"/> Howe be it, when the gaynes ſhoulde be parted, then all the coſtes and charges ought to be deducted from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and then ought the reſydue of the gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be diuined, &amp; this might be borne, for he may bring that thynge to paſſe with thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, which otherwiſe he could not haue done. But what, and if he do not onely winne no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng, but alſo ſuffereth loſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Whether he wynne or loſe, I haue nought to do withall. If he wynne, I will haue halfe part, or a certayn ſumme apoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted betwene vs. If he wynne nothinge, or elles be a loſer, I will haue my head money har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meles, and without any loſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:77"/>
               <p>This is a good neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touche. Thou wylt loke for gaynes, but thou wilt beare no loſſe. Is thy money better and more precious, then his body and lyfe? Was the money ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de for mans ſake, or ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys ſake? If it be a fellowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe, there muſt an equal pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be kept, and not the one to ſtande to the gaynes onely, and the other to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe alone. Yea thou with thy money ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghteſt rather to the loſſe then he with his body. For thou ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yeſt gette other money, but he can not gette another body, nor yet his health ſo eaſely, yf he chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe to be diſeaſed for takyng of thought or feare or ſuche li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. And albeit that the lawes in this caſe do graunte, that he
<pb facs="tcp:10377:77"/> ſhall kepe touche with the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to his promiſe, yet do not they ſpeake it becauſe they prayſe or allowe ſuche fellowe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhippe (for they call it playne robberye, and a theuyſhe fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe as hath bene declared aboue) but becauſe he hath ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de a promiſe, whiche he ought to kepe. And becauſe no man ſhoulde lyghtely preſume to breake his promyſe. If a man maye ſell all his goodes,<note place="margin">Vid. Inſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutiſtas d. §. nam &amp; ita. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt. de So<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> etc.</note> rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes titels and intereſtes of the ſame, accordinge as the caſe re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quireth, why ſhoulde it not be lawful for him alſo to make ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract as this is? Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore if he do make it, why ſhuld he not kepe it? But this clauſe woulde do very wel by it, that he did it with his owne good wyll. For I feare leaſt he haue
<pb facs="tcp:10377:78"/> done it againſt his wyl, and ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue bene compelled to do it for the obtayninge of thy money. So that it be therfore turned agayne into violence, and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery. If he haue done it with his good will, it is reaſon that he kepe it, and if he haue bene conſtrained to do it, not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough any compulſion, but for his lukers and profites ſake, then muſt he nedes ſtande to it and kepe it. But take thou hede howe thy conſcience is in quiete. Thou bieſt of him with thy money his ſweate and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure. If thou wilt perpende the matter accordingly, thou ſhalt fynde whether thou coul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt be content thy ſelf to be ſo dealth withall, or not. Bothe the ſpirituall lawe and alſo the temporall lawe concludeth by
<pb facs="tcp:10377:78"/> the lawe of nature, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which wil haue profite and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modite, muſt alſo beare parte of heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Wherfore yf thou wilt ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue gaynes, then muſt thou alſo abide the daunger of it, or els it is but more vſurye and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berye. But this were honeſt, if thou wouldeſt lende a manthy money, or put it into his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and ſaye, my frende, occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pie this with all diligence poſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, doynge thyne endeuour to the vttermoſte of thy pouer, yf thou gette ought with it, then will I haue thus muche of the gaynes accordinge to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſumme. If thou get nothynge, then will I gette no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynge. But if thou be a loſer by it, and the faulte be in the, beare it alone. But if the faulte be not in the, &amp; that ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rfotune
<pb facs="tcp:10377:79"/> or other caſualtie hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto it, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil I beare part agayne of the loſſe. For if thou wilt beare no loſſe nor ſtande in any daunger at all, what is it elles but vſurye whatſoeuer thou takeſt more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt lent? What is ſuche a contract elles but a putting furth of thy money for a certayne aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, as other vſurers do? yea &amp; although thou adde vnto it, if he get nought, I get nought alſo, yet doeſt thou hope for v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury &amp; that is vſury, although it be ſomewhat more honeſt &amp; clenlyer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>What and if I ſhoulde take ſomuche the leſſe gaynes to thintent that he ſhoulde beare the loſſe alone, yf any miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
<pb facs="tcp:10377:79"/> ſhoulde chaunce?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Of this haſt thou hearde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue. Whatſoeuer thou takeſt, if thou ſtande in no dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, but ſitteſt at home in thy chyer, or if thy money be aſſured vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> then is thy money lent vpon vſury. For all be it that a mans labour and paynes maye be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced with money, yet are not all thinges cleare, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be done here after a ſorte, for thou haſt a diſſembler in thy boſome, called Auarice, whiche reſiſteth the ſtrongely. If thou do paye hym for hys paynes, ſorowe and care, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de then I let it paſſe. But if thou do it not, thou art an vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rer. But howe canſt thou bye of a man his fortune, and paye him for his chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces or miſchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:10377:80"/> which neither thou nor he knoweth as yet? He maye pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe it the and if he do, he muſt perfourme it, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre thou the caſe and iudge in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience whether thou wouldeſt thinke it good reaſon, yf the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ſhuld chaunce vnto the. He muſt nedes kepe touche becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe of his promiſe by the vertue of the contracte, But knoweſt thou not that a ſtrayght lawe is oftentymes tourned into a large wronge? And that to ſharpe cauſeth ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many gap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes? As Doctor Luthers wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des do ſounde. Therefore I ſaye, it is very ſtraunge and al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo very daungerous for thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience to occupie after that ſorte. Howe be it thou mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt make ſuche a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracte and alſo kepe it vntill thou ſaweſt
<pb facs="tcp:10377:80"/> ſome miſfortune, but thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeſt be no diſſembler as hath bene often ſayde. If thou wilt be an vſurer, thou mayeſt here brynge it to paſſe well ynough without correction of the hyer powers. But God is a rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Truely Paſquill, thou haſt layde ſuche a foundacion, that whoſoeuer then buyldeſt ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on muſt ſtande. Thou haſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me inſtruction out of the lawes, what vſurye is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>(Deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.)</hi> quiae ſpes &amp; expec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tatio lucri facit Vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. de ſi faenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueris <hi>14.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> ex de Vſuris c. Conſtituit</note> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whatſoeuer is deſyred or ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken aboue the head ſumme, ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng no maner exception, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where there is auenture or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour concurring. Whatſoeuer I do obiecte, there is no caſe ſo ſtraunge, but it maye be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thereafter. For thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:10377:81"/> layde by it a good pair of balau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, namely the conſcience. He that wylbe an vſurer, maye do it, neither is it poſſible for the magiſtrates ſo narrowely to loke vpon it, that all practiſes and ſubtelties ſhoulde be left.</p>
               <p>But he that wilbe good, and no vſurer, maye by this our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munication, take a ſufficient in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>In dede it is cleare &amp; plaine ynough for hym that wyll ſee, marke, and receyue, and wyll amende his lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Verely it is a piteous caſe to ſe that this enormitie is ſo generall. But I praye the tell me one thynge, I haue ſufficiently perceyued by the
<pb facs="tcp:10377:81" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſcriptures of God and alſo by the conſtitucions of mannes la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes, that it is forbidden, but is there any paine or penaltie pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Aſkeſt thou yet whether there be any penaltie preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed or not? thinkeſt thou that although there were no payne at all named, that thou nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not to feare ynough, conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derynge that thou haſt heard ſo euidently and knoweſt ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is bothe againſt God and againſt the hyer powers? Thou arte not ignoraunt I am ſure, what he deſerueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wittingly doth againſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes and manifeſt will of God. Thou knoweſt it I ſaye, yf thou wouldeſt beleue it. But beholde I wyll name
<pb facs="tcp:10377:82"/> the ſaide punyſhementes and paynes vnto the.</p>
               <p>The Emperours Maieſtie hath concluded and commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded by thaduiſe and will of the whole Empire in the parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holden at Auſburgh in the yere of our lord .MD.xxx That no maner contracte par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticipatinge or hauinge any fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweſhippe with vſury ſhould be admitted &amp; alſo that all the ſame ſhould be taken as voyde and of none effecte. And that if any man dyd make or vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuche contracte ſhoulde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fait to his magiſtrate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth parte of his head ſumme with out redemption, and ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be punyſhed. Lo this is but a money payne But howe, and if I proue vnto the that an vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rer is a robber? For whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:10377:82" rendition="simple:additions"/> is taken from any man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerued againſt his will, the ſame is robbery. But the vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers take a mans goodes or money from hym by compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt his wyll, therfore are they robbers. That they do compel a man to geue them his money and take it by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is manifeſt, for the poore man is loth to do it, and yet he can not chuſe, but muſt do it for the vſurers do compel hym to it, and not his nede. His nede compelleth hym to borrowe. Nowe he might borrowe well ynough (as pertainynge to his wyll) without paynge any vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, yea and he woulde alſo do it fulfayne. But then commeth the vſurer and compelleth him to the geuing of vſury, and vio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lently taketh his goodes from
<pb facs="tcp:10377:83"/> hym. Nede conſtrayneth hym to borrowe, and this is no leſſe to hym, but vſury putteth him to loſſe. For yf he will borrowe he doth it of neceſſite, but the vſurer compelleth hym to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue money for it,<note place="margin">Ieſus Sprach calleth ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therers, and not worthy to kepe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany with chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten men</note> not by playne and manifeſt violence, but by ſubtell meanes and neceſſities. Therfore is an vſurer a rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as thou haſt hearde aboue, and is alſo worthy to haue a robbers punyſhement. Item an vſurer is a thefe, wherfore he hath deſerued hangynge. That he is a thefe is manifeſt by the dede, as hereafter apea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth playnely in the vſurers confeſſion. Wherfore he is wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy alſo to haue the punyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a thefe. Therfore yf he be lyke vnto them both, as he is in dede, than is he alſo
<pb facs="tcp:10377:83" rendition="simple:additions"/> accurſed and not worthy to eate or to drynke with any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man: And theſe are the pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſhementes of the temporall lawes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De</hi> Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris in ut etc.</note> The eccleſiaſticall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an vſurer ought not be buried with &amp; as other Chriſten men, vntyll he haue made reſtitucion of al thynges gotten by the waye of vſurye. And that although he ſhoulde commaunde his executours in his dead bedde to do the ſame, yet ought he to remayne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buried, or not to be buried by &amp; as other Chriſten men, vntil it were done in dede or elles ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient aſſuraunce were made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernyng the ſame. The ſame lawe ſhewed alſo howe, when and howe farre the ſame reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucion muſt be made, namely as farre as all hys goodes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende.
<pb facs="tcp:10377:84"/> But I feare that this wil not ſo ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly come to paſſe. Alſo a mans owne conſcience doth ſufficiently inſtructe him, and it is ſufficient that the vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rer knoweth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy buried by other Chriſten men, before he haue made reſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tucion of al, wherfore I thinke it not neceſſary here to be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this time. Furthermore the eccleſiaſticall lawes wil that no vſurer ſhould be abſolued nor admitted to beare witnes in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matter, nor make any teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or laſt wil, nor ſuffered to haue any fellowſhyppe with other Chriſtians,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> quia in omnib. ex de Vſuris C. Prete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea ex de Vſuris. Gloſ. in d<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>e. ſi quis.</note> in the vſe of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes or otherwyſe. But ſhuld be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated &amp; accurſed out of al Chriſten fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhippes, and here is he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a thefe and a robber. Lo, is
<pb facs="tcp:10377:84"/> not this alſo ſhame ynough? Is not this punyſhement, of the eccleſiaſticall lawes ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent?</p>
               <p>But what is the punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God? Euen hell ſyre, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtinge damnation. For it is euident ynough that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer doth wittingly agaynſt his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, and againſt his holy worde, and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſydes that againſt the hier po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, becommeth no Archau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, but perpetual kynſman of the deuill in hell fyre, as it is taught in diuers places of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptur. Nowe is it certain and ſure, that an vſurer dothe wittingly againſt all theſe, as hath bene ſufficiently declared aboue both out of holy ſcriptur and alſo out of the lawes both temporall &amp; alſo eccleſiaſticall,
<pb facs="tcp:10377:85"/> wherefore there is no doubte, but he goeth after this lyfe ſtrayght waye to the deuill. What ſayeth the lorde by the mouthe of the Prophete Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiell?<note place="margin">Ezec. <hi>18</hi>
                  </note> If any man lende vpon vſury and take more ouer,<note place="margin">Ezec. xxij</note> ſhal he lyue?<note place="margin">He that will not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by this text, onely v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon hym is all la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour loſt for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill hath ſurely ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken hym bodely &amp; blynded him with couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes.</note> He ſhall not lyue, but ſhall dye, and his bloude ſhal be vpon hym, ſaith the lord. And agayne, thou haſt taken vſury and increace, thou haſt oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thy neyghbours by extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, and forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me ſaith the lorde God. Behold I haue ſmi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten my handes vpon thy coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes that thou haſt vſed. Is thy harte able to endure it, or may thy handes defende them ſelues in the tyme that I ſhall brynge vpon the? Euen I the lorde that ſpake it will bring it alſo to paſſe. I wyll ſcatter the
<pb facs="tcp:10377:85"/> amonge heathen &amp; ſtrowe the about in the landes and wyll cauſe thy fylthines to ceaſe out of the: yea and I will haue the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſight of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then, that thou mayeſt knowe that I am the lorde. Lo if God be ſo wroth with his owne cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen people for vſuries and coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>touſnes ſake threateninge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſo cruell punyſhemente what ſhall happen vnto the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge a ſtraunger? By this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeſt thou perceiue eaſely what puniſhement God hath ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for vſurers, namely, hell fyre, and euerlaſtyng payne, as thou haſt hearde playnely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Of a trueth Paſquill, thou makeſt me to ſweate. For after this maner ſhould be nothyng worſe, nor more pernicious
<pb facs="tcp:10377:86"/> more execrable, deteſtable and ſynful then an vſurer. In dede it is cleare and manifeſt that vſury is againſt the lawe of na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, the lawe of God written, and againſt the lawes both te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and eccleſiaſticall. Thou haſt alſo partely reherſed vnto me the puniſhementes belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge to the ſame. Inſomuche that a man might be afraied of an vſurer, neither were it any maruail though mendid ſpitte at hym in the ſtretes. If the la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes take an vſurer for a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer a robber, a thefe, a vilay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and a damnable perſone, as it is manifeſt by the ſcripture &amp; alſo by the lawes. A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might rather haue to do with a Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, and a Panyme then with a great vſurer. But thou ſaideſt euen now, that they ought not
<pb facs="tcp:10377:86"/> to be buryed among other chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians, where ſhoulde they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Knoweſt thou not this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, Similis ſimile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Lyke wyll to lyke ſayd the deuill to the Coiller, for they were both black. The lord cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them in Ezechiel extorcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, wherfor it is not againſt their dignitie to be buried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge theues &amp; robbers. For ſeyng they are not worthy to lye amonge other Chriſtians, they muſt nedes be layde in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me place agreinge to their qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lities.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Paſquil it were no maruail though one did deſpayre. I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue gotten many a fayre penny
<pb facs="tcp:10377:87"/> by vſury, yet woulde I neuer haue thought, that it had bene ſo great a ſynne, and ſuche an heathenyſhe, vngodly execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and damnable thyng. I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſerued many one vnder the pretence of frenſhyp, that he hath afterwardes felt it full well doubteles, and haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of a gifte ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked many a mans ſweate.</p>
               <p>When I lent a man my money I lent it hym but from one fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re to another, and whan I to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke hym the money, I deducted the encreaſe before hande, and made hym to ſeale me an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion for the hole ſumme, as though I had lent hym ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che and he was bounde to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre me no leſſe, ſo that no man founde any vſury nor increaſſe in my writynges. For I had
<pb facs="tcp:10377:87"/> receyued it afore hande. And thys dyd I from one fayre to another. For if I ſhoulde haue lent it hym for the ſpace of an hole yere, an ſhould haue requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red ſo muche at one tyme, it ſhould haue had ſome apearau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of vſury. Wherfore I take it thryſe, or foure tymes a yere, &amp; alwayes as muche in a maner as men were wont to take for an whole yere. Nowe yf I ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me into the fayre and required my money, my debter was bounde to pay it me: yf then he had ſo muche nede of it that I might perceiue it, then was he fayne to greaſe my hande, yea many one hath ben compelled to geue it me againe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I kept it but one daye, leaſt he ſhould haue bene ſuſpected, and then I lent it hym agayne as I dyd
<pb facs="tcp:10377:88"/> before. Somtyme I dyd ſet hym a daye after the fayre, not paſt a fourtenight or three or foure wekes at the moſte, and where as he was bounde afore to paye me nobles, he was bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de at that daye to paye me an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellottes. And then I le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hym my money agayne, as before. So that I haue oftentymes made thyrty of the hundred or rather more. Yea often haue I lent in ſuche wyſe that my det<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was not excuſed with forty crownes in a yere, &amp; yet coulde I make it a pretence and appea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunce of frenſhyppe, amitie &amp; loue, as ſuche my practiſes of bad &amp; good money are almoſt knowen to all the worlde, and alſo partely ſet in printe, if ama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would loke ouer al the bookes that of late haue bene written
<pb facs="tcp:10377:88"/> againſt vſury, as the two boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of Doctor Martyn Luther, the one of marchaundiſe and vſury, and the other to the Curates and Paſtours, of vſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, the boke of doctor Hepium vpon the .xv. Pſalme, the boke of doctor Iames ſchenken of the couetouſnes of Iudas, the boke of Iohn Spangenbergh of almoſe and others, and alſo this our communication. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it were no maruayll, though an vſurer ſhoulde diſpayre, &amp; hange hym ſelfe by the necke, or that an other man ſhoulde ſpitte al vſurers in their faces. Whiche in dede Paſquill gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth my very ſore, not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing howe to behaue my ſelfe. I am afrayd truely that I ſhal neuer come to God. So much do I fele already.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:10377:89"/>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Ah good fellowe what ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keſt thou of thy grefe?<note place="margin">Ezech. XViij.</note> yf thou wilt be good, if thou wilt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued returne. Saieth not the lorde, turne and ye ſhal liue? If thy grefe be ſo greate, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, rendre agayn that thou haſt ſtolen, and be a good man, &amp; God wilbe merciful vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vſurer.</speaker>
               <p>Alas Paſquil I would ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe with a good will, but the ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drynge agayne is to harde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <p>Aha, I thought as muche, that it was but a fayned repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce thou arte afrayde, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that feare doeſt thou repente. But thou kepeſt faſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodes of vſury, &amp; letteſt the feare paſſe, yea y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodes are in
<pb facs="tcp:10377:89"/> thy waye, ſo that thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not paſſeouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Well then get y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hence to the deuill in the name of al deuils. And there an end. I can no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger talke with the, For all is but labour loſt. Yet will I in time conuenient ones more geue to the vſurers a bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of roddes, yf God lende me witte and diſcrecion. Thou knoweſt that I haue had this my communication with the vnaduiſedly, in haſt, which not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding I wil alſo ſetfurth to thintent that thou and thy frendes maye haue ſomething to paſſe the tyme withall. And it ſhalbe geuen to the and all vſurers for a breakefaſt, vntill by the grace of God, it ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:10377:90"/>
            <head>Concluſion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I haue in ſome places ſet certayne allegations or anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, was done for this purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, that the vſurers ſhould vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande that it is grounded vpon the holy ſcripture and in the lawes, whatſoeuer herein is intreated and ſpoken of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quillus. And likewyſe that they do wittingly againſt God the father and his onely ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, and his holy eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and cleare worde, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo againſt the temporall and ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall magiſtrates, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue at Goddes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d worthely deſerued the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of hel fyre, and at the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:10377:90" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the temporall magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes the punyſhement of loſyng both honour body and goodes with other corrections.</p>
            <p>And this be geuen vnto the great money vſurers, hel mou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes, helhoundes and beare-wolues for a fayringe. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe if there were any man whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience were touched by his writinge or by the holy ghoſt, whiche ſeldome happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to a ryght vſurer, let him learne to aſke counſayll and to ſeke comforte, where he ought to ſeke it, namely of Goddes worde and the miniſters of the ſame. For if there be an earneſt repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, he ſhall fynde both counſall and comforte doubte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. But if it be a coloured re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce, whiche laſteth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he is out of the Churche, or
<pb facs="tcp:10377:91"/> meteth with ſome that haue nede of money, then ſhall he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo fynde it where as other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly people do fynde it. For although he deceiue Goddes miniſter, and ſo other men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour of holynes, yet ſhall he neuer be able to decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue God, who iudgeth the hart, and ſeeth in ſecrete as the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſayth. Neither wil he be made a lyer for hym, but will ſuffer hym to dye euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly, and his bloude to be vpon hym, as he ſaith by the prophete Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by Steuen Mierdman. <hi>1550.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10377:91"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
